<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the third of March, 1610. By Theophilus Higgons. In testimony of his heartie reunion with the Church of England, and humble submission thereunto. Published by command</title>
            <author>Higgons, Theophilus, 1578?-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03336</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13456</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104096</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839835</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839835</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4291</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03336)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4291)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1106:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the third of March, 1610. By Theophilus Higgons. In testimony of his heartie reunion with the Church of England, and humble submission thereunto. Published by command</title>
                  <author>Higgons, Theophilus, 1578?-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Hall, for William Aspley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In this edition, title page verso has apology for errata "in the former impression .. in this second .. corrected".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Higgons, Theophilus, 1578?-1659.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4291:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4291:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED at Pauls <hi>Croſſe</hi> the third of March, 1610.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Theophilus Higgons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In teſtimony of his heartie reunion with <hi>the Church of England, and humble</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion thereunto.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Command.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MICAH 7.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Reioice not againſt me, ô mine enemie: though I fall, I ſhall riſe againe; when I ſhall ſit in darkeneſſe, the Lord ſhall be a light vnto me.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Imprinted by WILLIAM HALL, for <hi>William Aſpley.</hi> 1611.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4291:2"/>
            <p>GEntle Reader, whereas in the former impreſsion, by reaſon of importunate haſte of the Worke, ſome few faults eſcaped, and eſpecially, page <hi>4.</hi> l. <hi>22.</hi> in this ſecond thou ſhalt finde them corrected. Farewell.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:4291:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED AT PAVLS Croſſe, the third of March. 1610.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>EPHES. 2. verſ. 4.5.6.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> But God, who is rich in mercy, through his great loue, wherewith he loued vs,</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Euen when we were dead by ſinnes, hath quickned vs together in Chriſt, by whoſe grace you are ſaued,</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> And hath raiſed vs vp together, and made vs ſit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the heauenly places, in Chriſt Ieſus,</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> That he might ſhew, in the ages to come, the excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding riches of his grace, through his kindneſſe towards vs in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is a fourefold condition, or eſtate of Man. The firſt of <hi>Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy:</hi> the ſecond, of <hi>Sinne:</hi> the third, of <hi>Grace:</hi> the fourth, of <hi>Glory.</hi> The firſt, by creation from God: the ſecond, by propagation from our Parents: the third, by regeneration from the Spirit: the fourth, by reall poſſeſſion of Heauen.</p>
            <p>Now as the ſubſtance of my text leadeth me to entreate, peculiarly, of the third conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or eſtate (which is the ſtate of <hi>Grace</hi>) ſo the very firſt word, and entrance thereof [BVT: a diſcretiue particle] directeth me vnto a conſideration of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4291:3"/> our ſecond eſtate; to wit, the ſtate of <hi>Sinne:</hi> which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle deſcribeth in this manner.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>And you hath he quickned, that were dead in treſpaſſes, and ſinnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Wherein, in times paſt, you walked according to the courſe of this world, and after the Prince, that ruleth in the aire, euen the ſpirit, that now worketh in the children of diſobedience:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Among whom we alſo had our conuerſation, in times paſt, in the luſts of our fleſh, in fulfilling the will of the fleſh, and of the mind, &amp; were, by nature, the children of wrath, as wel as others.</hi> It followeth, now, in my Text: <hi>But God who is rich in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the connexion, and dependency of theſe wordes. Before, there was the ſtate of <hi>Sin,</hi> here is the ſtate of <hi>Grace,</hi> the one oppoſed vnto the other; whereby the deformity of the firſt, &amp; dignity of the ſecond, doth more ſpectably ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For in the former, we learne what we were by nature (corrupted, not created nature) in the other we learne what <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> we are by grace. In the former we behold our owne miſery: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> in the ſecond we contemplate the mercy of God. In the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer we ſee our captiuity: in the ſecond our deliuerance. In <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the former we ſee our death in ſinne: in the ſecond, our life in Chriſt. Therfore excellently ſaith our Apoſtle: <hi>Where ſin abounded there grace abounded much more: that, as ſinne had raigned vnto death, ſo might grace alſo raigne, by righteouſnes, vnto eternal life, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord:</hi> Rom. 5 20.21.</p>
            <p>Thus the ſtate of <hi>ſinne,</hi> in time, and order, is before the ſtate of <hi>Grace:</hi> as the euening was before the morning (Gen. 1.5.) and the darkenes before the light. <hi>You were once darkenes: but now you are light in the Lord.</hi> Epheſ. 5.8.</p>
            <p>For ſome liued without the Law, as <hi>Gentiles:</hi> ſome vnder the Law, as <hi>Iewes:</hi> now both are vnder grace. But it is one thing to be <hi>in</hi> grace, another thing to be <hi>vnder</hi> grace. Many liue now <hi>vnder</hi> grace, but not <hi>in</hi> it: many liued heretofore <hi>in</hi> grace, but not <hi>vnder</hi> it. For (properly) to liue <hi>in</hi> grace, is oppoſed vnto the ſtate of ſinne: to liue <hi>vnder</hi> grace, is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed vnto the ſtate of the Law. The firſt is the ſtate of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4291:3"/> 
               <hi>perſons,</hi> who haue grace dwelling in them: the ſecond is the ſtate of <hi>time,</hi> wherein grace is offered vnto all.</p>
            <p>Both are ioined heere together in my Text. The ſtate of <hi>time;</hi> we are vnder grace: the ſtate of <hi>perſons;</hi> wee are in grace: ſo that we are deliuered from the power of the law, and of ſinne; from the condemnation of the firſt, and from the dominion of the ſecond. <hi>Sin</hi> preuaileth not to domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: why? we are in grace. The <hi>Law</hi> preuaileth not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation: why? we are vnder grace. And this is the ſcope of my Text.</p>
            <p>Wherein there is ſuch amplitude, and varietie of matter, that plenty it ſelfe hath made mee poore, it being hard to ſay, where, and whence I ſhould take the beginning of my diſcourſe: as alſo it is hard to ſay, where I may conclude the ſame. But ſince the time hath power ouer my thoughts (at the leaſt ouer my words) and boundeth them within the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of an houre, or two; I cannot ſpeake all of a little in my Text, as I would: therfore I will ſpeake a little of all therein, as I may; obſeruing fiue generall circumſtances, as they preſent themſelues in order vnto your view.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, the Author of our ſaluation; God: or God in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Chriſt. For <hi>God was in Chriſt, reconciling the world vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</hi> 2. Cor. 5.19.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, the cauſes, which mooued God vnto this <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> excellent worke: and they are three. Firſt, <hi>Mercy:</hi> v. 4. not bare mercy, but with an addition, <hi>rich</hi> in mercie. Secondly, <hi>Loue:</hi> and that not a naked loue, but with an addition, <hi>great</hi> loue. Thirdly, <hi>Grace</hi> iv. 5. not ſimply grace alſo, but with an addition, <hi>exceeding riches</hi> of his grace. v. 7. And here, with this motiue, or cauſe, I will ioine the effect alſo: <hi>by grace you are ſaued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third is, the perſons, or ſubiect, vpon which the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> are conferred; <hi>Vs.</hi> Wherein you may obſerue; Firſt, the extenſion of the ſubiect: to wit, <hi>Iewes,</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> both included therein. Secondly, the condition: <hi>dead in ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth is, the benefits beſtowed vpon vs: and they <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> are three. Firſt, viuification of the ſpirit: <hi>Hee hath quickned
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4291:4"/> vs together in Chriſt.</hi> verſ. 5. Secondly, reſurrection of ſoule, and body: <hi>He hath raiſed vs vp together:</hi> verſ. 6. Thirdly, Seſſion of both in heauen: <hi>He hath made vs ſit together in the heauenly places, in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Fifth, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> and laſt is, the end, and finall cauſe of all this happineſſe towards vs, and indulgence from God: <hi>That he might ſhew in the ages to come, the exceeding riches of his grace, through his kindnes towards vs in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Firſt of the <hi>Author.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Author of our ſaluation is he, that is the author of our creation; GOD. <hi>Non eſt qui reficiat, niſi qui fecit,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard.</hi> None can make vs good of euill, but hee that made vs ſomething of nothing. It is he that, in my creation, <hi>dedit me mihi,</hi> gaue me vnto my ſelfe, by creating me after his owne image. It is he that, in my Redemption, <hi>dedit ſe mihi,</hi> gaue himſelfe vnto me, by redeeming mee with his owne bloud.</p>
               <p>But you muſt vnderſtand, that this ſacred name of GOD, is taken ſometimes <hi>eſſentially,</hi> ſometimes <hi>perſonally:</hi> and this is neceſſary to be knowne in the explication of my text. <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially</hi> it includeth the three perſons, ſubſiſting in one vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuided nature: as Gen. 1.1. <hi>In the beginning,</hi> GOD <hi>created the heauen, and the earth.</hi> Therefore the originall hath it thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>creauit Dij:</hi> the Gods created. The noune is plurall, the verbe ſingular; to ſhew a trinity of perſons, in the vnity of eſſence.</p>
               <p>Sometimes this ſacred name is taken <hi>perſonally;</hi> importing one perſon of the diuine nature: as Iohn 1.1. <hi>In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with</hi> GOD: That is, the Sonne was with the Father. <hi>With</hi> him, becauſe <hi>from</hi> him. With him <hi>[Deus apud Deum]</hi> by eternall coexiſtencie: from him <hi>[Deus de Deo]</hi> by perſonall proceſſion. In which reſpect, preciſely the Father is not with the Sonne; the Father, and the Sonne are not with the holy Ghoſt; but the Sonne is with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4291:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> and the holy Ghoſt is with them both.</p>
               <p>For as God is the <hi>God of order</hi> in all his creatures, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall works; ſo he is a God of order in himſelfe alſo, and in his internall workes. There is a priority of order in the Father before the Sonne, and in them both before the holy Ghoſt. So that the Father, being the fountaine of the other, hath a prerogatiue of order in his perſon and conſequently a prerogatiue of order alſo, in this glorious name of GOD.</p>
               <p>And thus it is in my Text: GOD, <hi>who is rich in mercy:</hi> that is, the Father. For though it be true in faith, that euery perſon is equally mercifull, louing and gracious; yet, in this place, it is proper to ſay that God the Father is rich in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and great in loue, and exceeding in grace. For here is a neceſſary relation of one perſon to the other: <hi>God quickned vs in Chriſt:</hi> that is, the Father in the Sonne.</p>
               <p>Now to the matter it ſelfe. It is <hi>God</hi> that quickneth vs, raiſeth vs, &amp;c. not <hi>Angels,</hi> not <hi>Man,</hi> not his owne <hi>Works,</hi> not his owne <hi>Will.</hi> Not <hi>Angels;</hi> they are <hi>miniſtring ſpirits,</hi> Heb. 1.14. not quickning, not raiſing ſpirits. <hi>Suggerunt bonum, non ingerunt: hortantur ad bonum, non bonum creant,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard:</hi> They may exhort vnto good, by their ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, they cannot powre it into vs, by infuſion: they may perſwade it, they cannot create it in vs. Not <hi>Man</hi> himſelfe: for the wandring ſheepe ſought not the ſhepheard, but the carefull ſhepheard ſought out the ſheepe, Matth. 18.12. Not the <hi>Workes</hi> of man: for can a dead tree bring forth liuing fruit? or an euill tree good fruite? Matth. 7.18. Finally, not the <hi>Will</hi> of man: for we did not preuent God in deſire, but it is <hi>he, that worketh in vs both the will, and the deed, of his owne pleaſure,</hi> Phil. 2.13. For though in actions naturall, and ciuill, man hath a libertie of will, yet in actions ſpirituall, and ſupernaturall, his will is dead, vntill it bee reuiued by GOD.</p>
               <p>Thus, all other meanes excluded, God is the onely Agent in this great, and glorious worke. <hi>Saluation is of the Lord,</hi> Ionah 2.9. Therefore ſaith God vnto his people: <hi>I, euen I, am he, that putteth away thine iniquities, for my owne ſake, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4291:5"/> will not remember thy ſinnes:</hi> Eſay 43.25. <hi>I,</hi> with an ingemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>euen I;</hi> excluding all other meanes: <hi>for mine owne ſake;</hi> excluding all other motiues.</p>
               <p>And this point is excellently inforced by <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thus vnto the children of Iſrael, leſt they ſhould attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute that vnto themſelues which was due vnto God alone; <hi>The Lord thy God hath choſen thee to be a precious people vnto himſelfe, aboue all people, that are vpon the earth. The Lord did not ſet his loue vpon you, nor chuſe you, becauſe you were more in number then any people: for you were the feweſt of all people But becauſe he loued you, and becauſe he would keepe the oath which he had ſworne vnto your Fathers,</hi> Deut. 7.6.7 8. No merit in them, but grace in him: that ſo they might truely ſay; <hi>Not vnto vs, ô Lord, not vnto vs, but vnto thy name giue the glory,</hi> Pſalme 115.1.</p>
               <p>Now if the <hi>Iewes</hi> could plead nothing, but the loue of God, for his peculiar fauour, what can the <hi>Gentlies</hi> plead for themſelues alſo, but the ſame loue of the ſame God? Therefore ſaith our Apoſtle; <hi>God, who is rich in mercy,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>he hath quickened vs,</hi> &amp;c. So that now we are come from the <hi>Author,</hi> which is GOD, vnto the <hi>Motiues,</hi> which are, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Loue, and Grace in him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Secondly of the <hi>Motiues.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN theſe alſo there is an order, as well in the attributes of God, as formerly in his name. Here is <hi>Mercy</hi> releeuing vs, and cauſed by his <hi>Loue.</hi> Here is loue embracing vs, and cauſed by his <hi>Grace.</hi> Here is grace ſauing vs, and cauſed by his <hi>Goodneſſe.</hi> For ſome learned Diuines obſerue that theſe foure properties, <hi>Mercy, Loue, Grace,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> as they are very like in their effect toward vs, ſo they are all one in God, but yet with a difference of order. <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> is the cauſe of all the reſt, but immediatly of <hi>Grace;</hi> Grace is the cauſe of the other, but immediatly of <hi>Loue:</hi> Loue is imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly the cauſe of mercy. So, in God, his <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> is a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4291:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> cauſe only, and his <hi>Mercy</hi> an effect only: the other are cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and effect too. And this is a golden chaine: the firſt linke whereof is Goodneſſe in God: the laſt is Mercy, which reacheth vnto vs.</p>
               <p>Firſt, then, of MERCY, as it is here firſt placed in my Text. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> GOD who is <hi>rich in mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That there is <hi>mercy</hi> in God, it ſheweth the compaſſion of his nature; that hee is <hi>rich</hi> in mercy, it ſheweth the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance thereof. In both we haue a ſingular comfort. For be it, that he hath <hi>mercy,</hi> that is a comfort: but our comfort is greater, becauſe <hi>diues eſt,</hi> he is <hi>rich</hi> in mercie; for <hi>with him there is plentifull redemption:</hi> Pſal. 130.7. Or be it, that he is <hi>rich,</hi> it ſheweth an abundance, and ſufficiency in himſelfe. But where is our comfort? euen this: <hi>Diues eſt in miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> he is rich in <hi>mercy;</hi> the ſweeteſt propriety of his diuine nature. So then: He is not ſimply <hi>rich,</hi> but in mercie: nor hath he ſimply <hi>mercie,</hi> but is alſo rich therein.</p>
               <p>Which as it is abundantly diſcouered vnto vs by the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects thereof, ſo it is teſtified vnto vs by his owne mouth: and we know, that his teſtimony is true. For when God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from heauen (which deſcent was not by mutation of place, but by exhibition of preſence) and proclaimed his owne name, ſee what a ſtyle he giueth himſelfe: <hi>The Lord, the Lord, ſtrong, mercifull, gratious, ſlow to anger, abundant in goodneſſe, &amp; truth, reſeruing mercie for thouſands, forgiuing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inquitie, tranſgreſſion, and ſin, not making the wicked innocent, viſiting the iniquity of the fathers vpon their children, vnto the third, and fourth generation:</hi> Exod. 34.6.7.</p>
               <p>Conſider here, firſt, the proprieties themſelues: <hi>mercifull, gracious, ſlow to anger, abundant in goodneſſe, reſeruing mercy, forgiuing iniquity:</hi> vnto all theſe he oppoſeth two other; the one, negatiue; <hi>he maketh not the wicked innocent:</hi> the other, affirmatiue: <hi>he viſiteth iniquitie.</hi> Conſider, ſecondly, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the one, and other. His mercy extendeth vnto <hi>thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands:</hi> his iudgement, vnto <hi>three, or foure generations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is <hi>mercie,</hi> and <hi>riches</hi> of mercie. This therefore being ſo peculiarly annexed vnto the diuine nature: the Church,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4291:6"/> for many hundred yeeres, harh vſed that excellent Collect; <hi>O God, whoſe nature, and property is euer to haue mercy, &amp;c.</hi> And this bringeth vnto my remembrance the ſaying of <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi> (ſo much applauded by <hi>S. Auguſt. lib.</hi> 9. <hi>de Cruit. Dei</hi>) when hee pleaded before <hi>Caeſar,</hi> for the life, and liberty of <hi>Ligarius,</hi> his friend: <hi>O Caeſar</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>none of thy vertues is more admirable, or gracious then thy</hi> MERCIE. <hi>Men come neere vnto God in nothing ſo much, as in ſauing the afflicted. Thy fortune hath nothing greater, then that thou haſt power; thy nature nothing better, then that thou haſt will, to ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and to ſaue others.</hi> So I may ſay: of all Gods proprieties none is more admirable, and gracious, then his mercy. It is not his power, it is not his knowledge, it is not his wiſdome, but it is his <hi>Mercy,</hi> wherein we chiefely reioice. I ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire, if there were not mercy in him, ſince there is ſo much iniquity in me. <hi>But, becauſe of ſinners, hee ſhall be called mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull:</hi> 2. Eſdr. 8.31.</p>
               <p>Thus his mercy hath an aduantage, by our ſinnes, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, and to expreſſe it ſelfe. For though, in him, there is an <hi>habit</hi> (if I may ſo ſpeake) of mercy alwaies; yet the <hi>act</hi> of mercy requireth ſinne precedent in vs, which giueth mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and occaſion vnto the ſame. There is a double matter of mercie: the <hi>one,</hi> whence it proceedeth: the <hi>other,</hi> where it is ſhewed. The firſt is in God onely, the ſecond in vs. <hi>The heauens neede not the mercy of God</hi> (ſaith <hi>August. in Pſal.</hi> 32.) <hi>becauſe there is no miſery in them: but the earth needeth it; and where the miſery of man hath abounded, there the mercie of God hath abounded much more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If therefore, I haue committed ſinne, then I haue fit mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the declaration of his mercy. <hi>In this, ô Lord, thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhall be praiſed, if thou be mercifull vnto vs, who haue not the ſubſtance of good works:</hi> 2. Eſdr. 8.36. In truth, many haue the ſhadow, not the ſubſtance of good works.</p>
               <p>Now though <hi>it is an euill cauſe</hi> (ſaith <hi>Seneca) which requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth mercy,</hi> yet there is no cauſe ſo euill, which can deſpaire of mercy. For as I haue the matter of, or for mercy in me (to wit, my ſins) ſo, if I haue the means to apprehend this mercy
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4291:6"/> (which meanes is faith alone) the mercy of God ſhall bee commended through mine iniquity, and my owne ſinne ſhall turne to my owne ſafety. <hi>All things worke together for the beſt vnto them, that loue God, euen to them that are called of his purpoſe.</hi> Rom. 8.28. <hi>Omnia cooperantur,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> all things worke: <hi>etiam peecata Domine,</hi> euen our ſins alſo, ô Lord. For by ſinne, we haue experience of our infirmity; our infirmity draweth vs vnto humility; humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty lifteth vs vp vnto God: in God euery man hath his <hi>quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt,</hi> perfect reſt, and endleſſe peace.</p>
               <p>Thus it is true, that ſinne, which naturally, and of it ſelfe, worketh damnation, may occaſionally, and by accident, worke ſaluation alſo: but by his power, who brought light out of darkeneſſe, and worketh our good out of our own euill.</p>
               <p>I dare not, therefore, adde this grieuous ſin vnto my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinnes, to deſpaire of mercy. For as to commit a ſinne, it is the death of the ſoule, ſo to deſpaire of mercy, it is to deſcend into hell. And ſome feare not to affirme, that <hi>Iudas</hi> ſinned more, by deſpaire of mercy, then by treaſon againſt his Lord. <hi>For what is more ſacrilegious</hi> (ſaith <hi>Fulgentius) then to deny Gods mercy in forgiuing our ſins? If he be a skilfull phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, he can cure all our infirmities; if a mercifull God, hee can forgiue all our ſinnes. Therefore Dauid</hi> (Pſal. 103.) <hi>exhorteth his owne ſoule to praiſe the Lord, and again to praiſe the Lord. Why? He forgiueth all thy ſinne, &amp; healeth all thine infirmities. If this be ſo, let no man deſpaire of the phyſitian, and remaine in his ſicknes; let no man extenuate Gods mercy, and pine away in his ſinnes. For Chriſt died for ſinners:</hi> Rom. 5.8. <hi>And Chriſt came into the world to ſaue ſinners.</hi> 1. Tim. 1.15. If I were not a ſinner, he were not a Sauiour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qualecum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fit ergopeccatum</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Whatſoeuer then thy ſinne be, God can and will pardon it, if thou, by deſpaire, doeſt not cloſe vp his hands, and ſhut vp the gate of indulgency againſt thy ſelf.</hi> Finally, he concludeth his exhortation out of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Eſay 55.7. <hi>Let the wicked forſake his wayes, and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous his owne imaginations, and returne vnto the Lord:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4291:7"/> and he will haue mercy vpon him: and to our God, for he is very ready to forgiue.</hi> Yea, <hi>multus ad ignoſcendum:</hi> as he rendreth it neerer vnto the originall text. <hi>In hoc multo nihil deeſt, in quo eſt omnipotens miſericordia, &amp; omnipotentia miſericors.</hi> He can pardon: for his mercy is omnipotent: he will pardon; for his omnipotency is mercifull. Therefore let no man deſpaire.</p>
               <p>Thus <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> much of the firſt motiue, or cauſe: to wit, the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God. And ſo I come vnto the ſecond, which is his LOVE, as it followeth here in my Text—<hi>through his great loue, wherwith he loued vs, euen when we were dead by</hi> [or <hi>in] ſins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is <hi>loue</hi> the cauſe of <hi>mercy. I haue loued thee with an euerlaſting loue, therefore with mercy haue I drawne thee:</hi> Ierem. 31.3. The riuer of mercy iſſueth from the fountaine of loue. But of this I haue ſpoken <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 8.</note> before.</p>
               <p>Now for the Text it ſelfe, you may obſerue: Firſt: that this affection, or attribute, is comfortable, becauſe it is <hi>loue;</hi> ſpecially in God. Secondly, that this loue is commendable, becauſe it is <hi>great.</hi> Thirdly, that this greatnes is admirable, becauſe it is toward <hi>vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning the Firſt, to wit, the affection, or attribute, <hi>loue in God;</hi> the beloued diſciple teacheth vs, that <hi>God is loue</hi> 1. Io. 4.8. And ſo <hi>loue</hi> is attributed vnto him in the abſtract, becauſe it is in him, not as an accident, and by participati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but by eſſence, as S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeaketh diuinely of this, &amp; other properties in God. <hi>He loueth as charity, he knoweth as truth, he fitteth as equity, he ruleth as maieſty, he gouerneth as the beginning, he defendeth as health, he worketh as power, he reuealeth as light, he aſſiſteth as piety. All theſe things the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels doe, yea we alſo doe, but yet in an inferiour manner: not by that good which we are, or haue in our ſelues, but which we par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate of him.</hi> But it is otherwiſe in GOD: whatſoeuer is attributed vnto him, is God himſelf. For he is a ſimple, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compounded being, in whom all things are one. So that the variety of his attributes is not from a diuerſity of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in him, but of effects vnto vs. But J am confined vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Loue, therfore I will ſpeake particularly of it.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:4291:7"/>
               <p>He hath an <hi>immanent</hi> loue dwelling in him: &amp; ſo he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth himſelfe, by the neceſſity of his nature. He hath a <hi>tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſient</hi> loue proceeding from him: and ſo he loueth his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſome more, ſome leſſe, by the liberty of his will.</p>
               <p>He hath <hi>a generall</hi> loue vnto all: for all are his creatures, the works of his own hands. He hath a <hi>ſpeciall</hi> loue vnto ſome, according as his <hi>Image,</hi> in reſpect of their ſubſtance, is ſtamped in them; and as his <hi>likeneſſe,</hi> in reſpect of their qualities, is repreſented in them. For <hi>likeneſſe is the cauſe of loue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So then God loueth vs, as his creatures; but more as men. He loueth vs as men; but more as elected. He loueth vs, as elected; but more as iuſtified. And this loue, which he bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vnto vs, as actually iuſtified by Chriſt, hee declareth more in his work of our ſanctification by the Spirit. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the more holy wee are, the more hee loueth vs. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> doth excellently obſerue <hi>(tract in Ioh.)</hi> that <hi>God loueth the Humanity of Chriſt, more then any man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was full of grace, and truth.</hi> Ioh. 1.14.</p>
               <p>If therefore, we will obtain and retain the loue of God, we muſt be as he is; conforming our wils vnto the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his will, and be like vnto him in all things: <hi>merciful,</hi> as he is mercifull; <hi>louing,</hi> as he is louing; <hi>gratious,</hi> as hee is gratious; yea <hi>perfect</hi> as he <hi>is perfect:</hi> Math. 5 48. Not by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equation; that is beyond our power: but by imitation, that is our dutie. <hi>Be holy for I am holy:</hi> Leuit. 11.44.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond place. As before, this loue in God was a <hi>ſpeciall,</hi> and not a generall loue, ſo here it is not a little, but a <hi>great</hi> loue. For <hi>he is a great God, and a great King aboue all Gods.</hi> Pſal. 95.3. Likewiſe his loue is great aboue all loues. Therefore the <hi>vulgar</hi> readeth it thus: <hi>propter nimiam chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem:</hi> for his ouer much loue.</p>
               <p>In truth it is <hi>ouer much;</hi> beyond our deſert, and beyond our comprehenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> too. For what loue ſhal I compare vnto his loue? The loue of a WOMAN? It is great indeed: but yet the loue of <hi>Ionathan</hi> vnto <hi>Dauid</hi> was greater then it. <hi>Thy loue to mee was wonderfull, yea paſſing the loue of women:</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:4291:8"/> 2. Sam. 1.26. The loue of a MOTHER? Here is a greater de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, then in the former: but yet this loue is not ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and infallible, as Gods loue. <hi>Can a woman forget her child, and not haue compaſſion vpon the ſonne of her wombe? If they ſhould forget</hi> (as ſome may be, yea ſome haue beene ſo vnnaturall) <hi>yet will not I forget thee,</hi> ſaith God vnto his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate, and afflicted <hi>Sion.</hi> Eſay 49.15.</p>
               <p>Therefore, till you canne find, whom you may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with God, you ſhall find no loue, to bee compared with his loue.</p>
               <p>But now, to come vnto the third point. As the loue of God was commended before, from the quantity thereof, it beeing a <hi>great</hi> loue; ſo it is yet further comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded from the obiect thereof; <hi>Vs.</hi> Who? <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles.</hi> Of what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, or eſtate? <hi>Dead in ſinne.</hi> This was <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 5.</note> deſigned by me to be the third generall circumſtance of my Text, but I will intreat of it here, becauſe I am ſo happily inuited thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. —<hi>his great loue, wherewith hee loued vs, when wee were dead by ſinnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, I will conſider the Obiect it ſelfe, <hi>Vs:</hi> which, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion, doth include both <hi>Iew,</hi> and <hi>Gentile.</hi> Secondly, the quality thereof, <hi>dead in ſinne,</hi> or <hi>by</hi> ſinnes. And firſt of the Obiect; <hi>Vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O bleſſed S. <hi>Paul! Quid tibi, &amp; nobis?</hi> what haſt thou to doe with <hi>vs?</hi> It was thy priuiledge, &amp; not ours to ſay, <hi>They [the Iewes] are Hebrewes, ſo am I: they are Iſraelites, ſo am I: they are the ſeede of Abraham, ſo am I:</hi> 2. Cor. 11.22. But ſo were not <hi>we;</hi> the Gentiles. What is the reaſon, then, thou ſhouldeſt here include thy ſelfe in this extenſiue par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle; <hi>vs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The reaſons are many, but ſpecially three. The firſt is, the charity of S. <hi>Paul.</hi> For the voice of <hi>Faith</hi> is, EGO, I; with an appropriation vnto our ſelues. Faith draweth the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference of Gods promiſes vnto the center of our hearts. But the voice of <hi>Charity</hi> is, Not, we; with a communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto all. Therfore it is one note of charity, aſſigned by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. Cor. 13.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>it ſeeketh not her own things.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:4291:8"/>
               <p>Secondly, the ſpeciall intereſt of S. <hi>Paul</hi> in the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> whoſe Apoſtle he was by way of excellency, and preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, aboue all others. <hi>He is a choſen veſſell vnto me, to beare my name before the Gentiles:</hi> Act. 9.15.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, our communion in Chriſt. For, now, <hi>the ſtop of partition-wall was broken downe:</hi> Epheſ. 2.14. Now there was <hi>one ſhephard, and one ſheepfold:</hi> Ioh. 10.16 Now <hi>God had perſwaded Iaphet to dwell in the tents of Shem:</hi> Gen. 9.27. So that, now, there was no difference, no diſtinction; as our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle diuinely ſaith: <hi>There is neither Iew, nor Grecian, there is neither bond, nor, free, there is neither male, nor female; for you are all one in Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> Galath. 3.28.</p>
               <p>Why, then, ſhould one nation deſpiſe another, or why ſhould one man contemne an other? For as we are all one, by nature, in the firſt <hi>Adam;</hi> ſo we are all one, by grace, in the ſecond. The nobility of ſtocke, the antiquity of deſcent, the abundance of wealth, the excellency of wit, the comeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of bodie; finally, no externall glory of temporal things maketh a difference, or an acception of perſons in the ſight of God.</p>
               <p>Now to proceede vnto our owne vnworthineſſe, whereby the worth of Gods loue is amplified; be we <hi>Iewes,</hi> or be we <hi>Gentiles,</hi> great was the loue of God, which was extended ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the one, or other.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Iewes;</hi> the whole courſe of the old Scriptures doth ſo demonſtrate their ingratitude, and rebellion againſt God, that it muſt needs be a ſingular, extraordinarie loue in him to vouchſafe them any grace, or fauour at all. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, I remit you vnto the 78. Pſalme, where the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> doth illuſtrate the benignitie of God, by the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this people: to wit, how hee brought them out of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt by a miraculous power, diuided the ſea for their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, brought water out of the ſtonie rocks for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, went before them in a cloud for their direction; <hi>yet they ſinned ſtill againſt him, and prouoked the Higheſt in the wilderneſſe,</hi> verſe 17. Notwithſtanding, hee rained downe <hi>Manna</hi> vpon them, he rained fleſh alſo vpon them, as duſt;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4291:9"/> 
                  <hi>yet, for all this, they ſinned ſtill, and beleeued not his wondrous works.</hi> verſ. 32. Notwithſtanding, he forgaue their iniquitie, and reſtrained his anger from them, vpon their ſubmiſſion vnto him: <hi>yet they returned, and tempted God, and limited the holy one of Iſrael,</hi> verſ. 41. Notwithſtanding, he caſt out the Heathen before them, to receiue them into their inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: <hi>yet they tempted, and prouoked the moſt high God, and kept not his teſtimonies.</hi> verſ. 56.</p>
               <p>But as for vs <hi>Gentiles,</hi> what could we plead? We were not the ſeede of <hi>Abraham:</hi> wee had not the ſeale of the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: the promiſes appertained not vnto vs: at leaſt, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the letter. All which things the <hi>Iewes</hi> might plead, as peculiar vnto themſelues alone. Therefore <hi>S. Paul</hi> hauing demanded, <hi>What is the preferment of the Iew?</hi> and <hi>what is the profit of circumciſion?</hi> anſwereth, <hi>Much euery manner of way, and chiefly, becauſe vnto them were committed the oracles of God:</hi> Rom. 3.1.2.</p>
               <p>But ſince wee <hi>Gentiles</hi> were not priuiledged by any of theſe graces, but were ſtrangers from the couenant, and wholly inthralled into the captiuitie of ſinne and Satan: heerein the loue of God is more ſpectable, and more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in vs, then in them, becauſe hee quickned <hi>Vs</hi> alſo, when we were dead in ſinne. So that now we are ſucceeded into the ſtate, nay more, into the very name of the <hi>Iewes</hi> themſelues. For <hi>hee is a Iew, who is one within:</hi> Rom. 2.28. And <hi>wee are the circumciſion, which worſhip God in the ſpirit.</hi> Philip. 3.3.</p>
               <p>For it is true (my brethren) that God delighteth not in outward things, without an inward affection; not in Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, not in Sacraments, not in Sacrifice, not in his owne People. Nay more: Chriſt acknowledgeth not the bleſſed Virgin to be his Mother, <hi>if ſhe heare not his word, and keepe it,</hi> Luke 8.21. Whereby he did not reproue her, but inſtruct others, in this behalfe.</p>
               <p>It is not therefore, ſucceſſion from worthy perſons, it is not birth from religious fathers, it is not the ſplendor, and dignity of a particular place, vpon which wee may ſecurely
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4291:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> reſt: yet theſe, theſe are things, and principall things too, wherein the Church of Rome doth ſo confidently repoſe. And as the literall <hi>Babylon</hi> (Eſay 47.8.) ſo ſhe, the myſticall <hi>Babylon</hi> (Apocal. 18.7.) glorieth in this manner, and ſaith; <hi>I ſit being Queene, and am no widow, and ſhall ſee no mourning.</hi> Howbeit her deſtruction is ordained of old, the ſentence of condemnation is paſt, the writ of execution is gone forth; <hi>The Kings of the earth ſhall hate the whore,</hi> [the ſometimes <hi>Mother</hi> Church now become a <hi>whore] and make her deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and naked, and ſhall burne her with fire:</hi> Apoc. 17.16.</p>
               <p>I come, now, from the Obiect, <hi>vs,</hi> vnto the quality there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; <hi>dead in ſinnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is a <hi>ſpirituall</hi> death of the ſoule: a <hi>temporall</hi> of the body: an <hi>eternall</hi> of both. I ſpeake not of the two latter, they are deaths <hi>for</hi> ſinne, not <hi>in</hi> ſinne: of which, alone, my text doth here peculiarly intreat.</p>
               <p>This <hi>ſpirituall</hi> death therefore of the ſoule in ſinne, is ſometimes in <hi>Thought</hi> onely; when we yeeld not conſent thereunto. For there is firſt, <hi>ſuggestion</hi> (either externally from Satan, or internally from our concupiſcence) then <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectation,</hi> and finally, <hi>conſent</hi> which properly bringeth ſin vnto her birth. Otherwiſe. S. <hi>Bernard</hi> asketh, in the perſon of a regenerate man; <hi>An forte iam non ago illa, ſed patior? ſi vtique non conſentio. Mea dixerim peccata, non quia facio, ſed quia ſuſtineo:</hi> I am rather a patient, then an agent in my ſinnes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Sometimes this ſpirituall death is in <hi>Action;</hi> to wit, <hi>tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſient</hi> action; for there was an <hi>immanent</hi> action before. For a ſinne may be actuall in the mind, though not acted in the body.</p>
               <p>Sometimes this ſpirituall ſinne is in <hi>Habit,</hi> and cuſtome; when ſinne is not only <hi>inhabitant</hi> (for ſo it is in all, though not imputed vnto all: it remaineth in act, not in guilt) but <hi>regnant</hi> in our ſoules. Of which our Apoſtle ſpeaketh in this maner: <hi>Let not ſinne raigne in your mortall body, that you ſhould obey it in the luſts thereof; neither giue you your members, as weapons of vnrighteouſneſſe, vnto ſinne:</hi> Rom. 6.12.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:4291:10"/>
               <p>All theſe deaths of the ſoule are figured, and repreſented in certaine perſons, whom our Sauiour raiſed vp from the death of the body. The firſt, in the Centurions daughter: Mark. 5.40. Her body lay yet in her fathers houſe; and there ſhe was raiſed vp vnto life. The ſecond, in the widowes ſon: Luke 7.12. His body was carried forth into the Citie, and there he was raiſed vp vnto life. The third, in <hi>Marthaes</hi> brother: Iohn 11.39. His body was laid in the graue, and there he was raiſed vp vnto life.</p>
               <p>Now our ſpirituall death was of the laſt, and worſt ſort. We were dead in the habit, and cuſtome of ſinne; dead in al our faculties and powers. Dead in the <hi>Will,</hi> which is the Queene-regent of the ſoule; dead in the <hi>Vnderstanding,</hi> which is her Counſellor; dead in the <hi>Memory,</hi> which is her Secretary; dead in the <hi>Affections,</hi> which are her meſſengers, and ſeruants. So dead in all, that ſinne raigned, and grace was extinguiſhed in our ſoules.</p>
               <p>And yet ô Lord, didſt thou loue vs when wee were dead men? Euen thou alſo, who art <hi>the God, not of the dead, but of the liuing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He did ſo, Brethren: our great ſinnes could not euacuate his good purpoſe. He loued vs in his election; then by mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation: the firſt, before all time; the ſecond, in time. And thus he was not changed by hauing loue now, which he had not euer, but we were changed by receiuing grace, which we had not before.</p>
               <p>Wherefore God loued vs, when we were ſpiritually dead: he loued vs, I ſay, in reſpect of his owne purpoſe, not of our works.</p>
               <p>And now as the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſpake literally of his owne greefe, but typically of Chriſts: Was there euer <hi>Dolor, ſicut dolor meus,</hi> griefe as my greefe? Lam. 1.12. So I may truly ſay of Gods loue: O Lord, was there euer <hi>Amor, ſicut amor <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uus,</hi> loue as thy loue? <hi>No man hath greater loue then this, that he lay downe his life for his friend:</hi> Iohn 15.13. It is true, no <hi>man</hi> hath greater: but thou, my <hi>Lord,</hi> hadſt grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; for thou laidſt down thy life for thine enemies. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4291:10"/> ſaith S. <hi>Paul; God ſetteth out his loue toward vs, ſeeing that, while we were yet ſinners, Chriſt died for vs.</hi> Rom. 5.8. While we were yet <hi>ſinners;</hi> dead in ſinne, and had no means to relieue our ſelues.</p>
               <p>For, if in our reſtitution vnto life, we had preuented God in deſire, or cooperated with him in act, his loue had not bin ſo ſet forth, as now it is. But the truth is, we were paſſiue, not actiue, in this excellent work; and ſo paſſiue, that there was nothing in vs, to concurre with God. It was not a ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and ſo we were awaked; it was not a wound, and ſo we were healed; but it was death, and ſo wee were raiſed vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: not by any vertue within vs, but by an externall power. For what motion, or actiuity is there in a dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, to raiſe vp it ſelfe? None. Therfore, as, in his creation, <hi>A dam was made a liuing ſoule, when God breathed the breath of life into him:</hi> Gen. 2.7. ſo, in his renouation (for he was an <hi>old Adam,</hi> as ſoone as hee was a <hi>new</hi>) God inſpired grace into him, and <hi>Adam</hi> was quickned againe from the death of the ſoule.</p>
               <p>Whereby, as we learne, how much we owe vnto God, &amp; how little vnto our ſelues, in this worke of our reſtitution vnto the life of grace; ſo we may behold, and hate the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitude, and deformity of ſinne, from this one effect, that <hi>it putteth vs in the ſtate of dead men:</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of the widow, liuing in pleaſure: <hi>ſhee is dead euen while ſhe liueth.</hi> A ſpirituall death in a naturall life. <hi>Thou haſt a name</hi> (ſaith God vnto the church of <hi>Sardis,</hi> Apocal. 3.1) <hi>that thou liueſt, but thou art dead.</hi> And ſo J may ſay vnto a ſinful man: it is but a name, a ſhadow of life, which thou haſt: for thogh thy body liue by thy ſoule, yet thy ſoule liueth not by grace: and conſequently, thou art ſeparated from GOD, the author and fountaine of thy life.</p>
               <p>Thus a ſinner is farre from God, and God is farre from a ſinner: the firſt in grace, the ſecond in mercy. But from whom God is farre in mercy, he is neer in iuſtice, for <hi>their deſtruction ſleepeth not.</hi> 2. Pet. 2.3.</p>
               <p>So much of the ſecond motiue, or cauſe, to wit, <hi>the great
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4291:11"/>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> loue of God, wherewith he loued vs when we were dead in ſinne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now enſueth the third, and laſt; namely GRACE; for ſo it followeth—<hi>by grace you are ſaued.</hi> Whereof I will intreat as briefly as I can.</p>
               <p>It may be a queſtion; why <hi>Not,</hi> before is now turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Vos?</hi> Before he ſaid, <hi>God loued vs;</hi> to wit, <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiles.</hi> Now he ſaith, <hi>You are ſaued;</hi> to wit, the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The anſwere is. Though Iewes and Gentiles haue a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon right in Chriſt, yet the right of the <hi>Iewes</hi> was more ſingular then ours, and in order, at the leaſt before ours, by reaſon of their priuiledges; as I ſhewed you before. Whence it is, that our Sauiour himſelfe teſtifieth in this manner; <hi>I am not ſent, ſaue to the loſt ſheepe of the houſe of Iſrael:</hi> Math. 15.24. Likewiſe he gaue his commiſſion vnto his diſciples; <hi>Goe not into the way of the Gentiles, but goe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto the loſt ſheepe of the houſe of Iſrael:</hi> Math. 10.5.6. Conformable whereunto is the teſtimony of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the vngratefull Iewes; <hi>It was neceſſary that the word of God ſhould firſt haue been ſpoken vnto you; but ſeeing you put it from you, and iudge your ſelues vnworthy of eternall life, loe wee turne vnto the Gentiles,</hi> &amp;c. Whereupon, the Gentiles glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified God, and receiued the Goſpell with great alacrity of heart; that ſo it might bee verified which the Prophet declared long before; <hi>Reioice ô barren, that didſt not beare: breake forth into ioy, and reioyce thou, that didſt not trauaile with child; for the deſolate hath more children then the marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed wif<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> Eſay 54.1. Specially therefore, <hi>the Gentiles were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But by what grace? There is the grace of God <hi>toward</hi> vs: which reſpecteth vs, as the obiects of it: there is the grace of God <hi>in</hi> vs, which reſpecteth vs, as the ſubiects of it. So that we are in the firſt grace, the ſecond grace is in vs. It is the firſt, therefore &amp; not the ſecond, by which we are ſaued. For we are not ſaued by the grace of God, wrought within vs by his Spirit, but ſhewed vnto vs in his Son. <hi>You are ſaued by grace;</hi> that is, by the free and voluntary fauour of God the Father, in Ieſus Chriſt his Sonne.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:4291:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>For the grace, of which S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth here ſpeake, is refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto God, euen the Father; howſoeuer our tranſlation (ſupplying ſome words, which are not in the originall) ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to refer it vnto the Son. But the matter is not great. For this <hi>grace</hi> is, equally, in all the perſons, but originally in the Father, exhibitiuely in the Son: by whom, and in whom, the Father hath declared his mercy, loue, and grace.</p>
               <p>To proceed then. <hi>We are ſaued by grace.</hi> What? by grace only? We are ſaued by Chriſt, by faith, by hope, by grace. By all theſe, but in a different manner. By <hi>Chriſts</hi> death, as the only meritorious cauſe: by <hi>Faith,</hi> as the proper inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall meanes: by <hi>Hope,</hi> Rom. 8.24. as ſuſtaining our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of things to come: by <hi>Grace,</hi> as mouing God.</p>
               <p>If therefore, the queſtion bee (as it is, properly, in this place) <hi>what was the firſt motiue of our ſaluation?</hi> The anſwere is, <hi>The grace of God.</hi> For as the end of our ſaluation is his glory, ſo the beginning of it is his grace. Our <hi>election</hi> to life is free: our <hi>vocation</hi> (inwardly by the ſpirit, outwardly by the word) is free: our <hi>iuſtification,</hi> by the bloud of Chriſt, is free: our <hi>ſanctification,</hi> by the holy Ghoſt, is free: finally, our <hi>glorification,</hi> in heauen, is free alſo; as <hi>Fulgentius</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth very well: <hi>Datur, ex gratia, non ſolùm iuſtificatis vita ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, ſed etiam glorificatis vita aeterna:</hi> Not only a good life vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, who are iuſtified, but alſo eternall life vnto them, who are glorified, is giuen freely, and by the grace of God <hi>Not of works, leſt any man ſhould boaſt himſelfe:</hi> Epheſ. 2.9.</p>
               <p>This is the argument, vpon which S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth ſpend a great part of his Epiſtles: this is the thing, which he doth euery where inforce; to wit, <hi>the grace of God in Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O S. <hi>Paul.</hi> S. <hi>Paul! Vas miſercoridiae &amp; tuba gratiae,</hi> the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of mercy, and the trumpet of grace. For, in none, was the mercy of God more expreſſed, then in thee: and, in none was his grace more exalted, then by thee.</p>
               <p>And this he doth not to deſtroy <hi>actum operis,</hi> but <hi>opinio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem meriti:</hi> not the performance of good works, but the opinion of merit thereby: and ſpecially the merit of <hi>Condig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> defendeth preciſely in this
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4291:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſenſe; to wit, that, after the <hi>firſt iuſtification,</hi> by Chriſt (the <hi>ſecond</hi> being by works, as they teach) a man, being in ſtate of grace, may performe (and ſome doe performe) ſuch good works, as, in their owne worth, and proper value, deſerue eternall life. This they call merit of <hi>Condignity.</hi> But this is an indignitie to God, a diſgrace to his grace, and blaſphemy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his honour. More truely ſaith our Apoſtle; <hi>Non ſunt condignae,</hi> &amp;c. the afflictions of this preſent life are not wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thie of the glory, which ſhall bee ſhewed vnto vs: Rom. 8.18 Neither our actions, nor our paſſions can deſerue the ſame. And I pray you marke the oppoſition in this behalfe. SVNT: <hi>they are worthy;</hi> ſaith the Church of Rome. NON SVNT: <hi>they are not worthy;</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Away, away with merit; let vs eſtabliſh the <hi>grace</hi> of God, which is more honourable vnto him, and more comfortable vnto vs. But J leaue the proſecution heereof, and, after a brief reflexion vpon that, which is already paſt, I will proceed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the reſidue of my text.</p>
               <p>Firſt, then, concerning the <hi>Mercy</hi> of God; Truſt in it, Truſt in it onely, Truſt in it euer. Truſt in it, without diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; for, <hi>in the mercies of the moſt High, you ſhall not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carrie:</hi> Pſalm 21.7. Truſt in it onely, without any other plea. <hi>We doe not preſent our ſupplications before thee for our owne righteouſneſſe, but for thy great tender mercies:</hi> Dan. 9.18. Truſt in it euer without wearineſſe; for <hi>his compaſſions faile not:</hi> Lam. 3.22. As the oyle did not ceaſe, till there wanted veſſels to receiue it; 2. King. 4.6. ſo there is no end of Gods mercy toward vs, till wee want faith to apprehend the ſame.</p>
               <p>Secondly, concerning the <hi>Loue</hi> of God; what ſhall wee render vnto him for the ſame? Loue for loue? That is moſt fit, ſince it is like for like. But though it bee like, yet it is leſſe. For as he goeth before vs in time [<hi>hee loued vs firſt:</hi> 1. Ioh. 4 19.] ſo hee excelleth vs in degree. He loueth vs more, then wee doe, or can loue him. Hee loueth vs, as a <hi>Father;</hi> we loue him, as <hi>Children.</hi> Ours is an aſcending, his a deſcending loue. But though we cannot loue him ſo much
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4291:12"/> as we ought, and as he loueth vs, yet let vs loue him aboue all things. <hi>Whom haue I in heauen, but thee? and, in earth, I haue deſired none, in compariſon of thee:</hi> Pſal. 73.25. Finally, let vs loue nothing but for him, <hi>Minùs te diligit, ô Domine, qui, praeter te<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> aliquid diligit, quod, propter te, non diligit:</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine:</hi> O Lord, he loueth thee leſſe then other things, who loueth any thing beſides thee, which he loueth not for thy ſake.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, concerning the <hi>Grace</hi> of God; it taketh away all our reioycing, but in him alone: who voluntarily, without our deſire, and freely, without our deſert, and entirely, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out our cooperation, hath ſaued vs by his grace, euen by his louing fauour towards vs, in Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <p>Therefore as I will not (nay I cannot) attribute any thing vnto my ſelfe, but weakeneſſe, and ſinne, which truly, and properly are my owne, (<hi>and if I muſt needs reioyce, I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce of mine infirmities:</hi> 2. Cor. 11.30.) ſo I will not put my confidence in man: for none is ſo great, or ſo good, that I may reſt ſecurely vpon his grace. But contrariwiſe, let the fooliſh deride me, the malitious depraue me, the inſolent contemne me, the mighty oppreſſe me, it is enough for me that I am in the grace, and fauor of my Lord. <hi>Sufficit mihi gratia tua:</hi> O Lord thy grace is ſufficient for me. I condlude therefore with S. <hi>Paul: Reioyce in the Lord alway, againe I ſay reioyce:</hi> Phil. 4.4.</p>
               <p>Thus I haue diſcourſed briefly vpon three circumſtances of my text. The <hi>Author</hi> of our ſaluation, GOD. The <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues</hi> in him, Mercy, Loue, and Grace. The <hi>Perſons,</hi> vpon which he hath conferred his benefits and fauours; Vs, dead in ſinne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the <hi>Benefits.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the fourth place, enſue the <hi>Benefits</hi> themſelues: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the firſt whereof is, <hi>Viuification</hi> in the ſoule; <hi>Hee hath quickened vs together in Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:4291:13"/>
               <p>Here is ſpirituall life oppoſed vnto ſpirituall death. It is comfortable becauſe <hi>Life,</hi> but more becauſe <hi>Spirituall:</hi> for this doth eleuate vs aboue our mortall condition, and is the pledge of our eternity in heauen.</p>
               <p>This ſpirituall life we haue partly in Chriſt, partly in our ſelues. In Chriſt, by iuſtification through his bloud. In our ſelues, by regeneration from the ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Firſt, by Iuſtification, through the bloud of Chriſt. For he, with all his merits, is ours. <hi>Thus I liue, yet not I now, but Chriſt liueth in me: and, in that I now liue, I liue by faith in the Sonne of God:</hi> Gal. 2.20. I am grafted into him, and ſo I liue by the life of the roote. His is the primitiue, mine a deriua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue life.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by regeneration from the Spirit, who ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth vs, and reneweth vs by grace. For as before, wee had <hi>imputed</hi> righteouſneſſe in Chriſt, ſo now wee haue <hi>inherent</hi> righteouſneſſe in our ſelues: though we are not thereby iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in the ſight of God, nor dare in any confidence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, appeare ſecurely in his preſence. <hi>Tutior mihi iuſtitia data, quam innata,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard:</hi> the imputed righteouſneſſe of Chriſt is more ſafe for me, then inherent righteouſneſſe from the ſpirit; that, which is <hi>on</hi> me, then <hi>in</hi> me. <hi>Iacob</hi> had not obtained the bleſſing, but in the garments of <hi>Eſau:</hi> Gen. 27.23. which was a type and figure of our happineſſe in the ſole righteouſneſſe of Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. Therefore S. <hi>Paul</hi> hauing <hi>eſteemed all things as dung, that he might win Chriſt,</hi> addeth: <hi>That I might be found in him, not hauing my owne righteouſneſſe, which is of the law, but that, which is through the faith of Chriſt:</hi> Phil. 3.9.</p>
               <p>Here, then, is life, to liue in him, who is life it ſelfe. <hi>I am the Way, the Truth, and the Life:</hi> Iohn 14.6. I am the <hi>Way,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which you wander. I am the <hi>Truth,</hi> without which you erre. I am the <hi>Life,</hi> without which you die.</p>
               <p>Let vs not, therefore, by ſinning any more, kill <hi>the Lord of life</hi> within vs, in whom, and by whom, we liue; neither let vs greeue the Spirit, by whom wee are ſealed vp vnto the day of redemption. Let vs not liue after the fleſh, and extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4291:13"/> the ſpirit: for <hi>the wiſedome of the fleſh is death: but the wiſedome of the ſpirit is life and peace,</hi> Rom. 8.6.</p>
               <p>It followeth,—he hath quickned vs <hi>together in Chriſt.</hi> Here is not onely life in vs, but a community of life with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by a myſticall vnion in Chriſt, and in our ſelues. For there is a double communion. The firſt, of the members with Chriſt. For as we haue a ſpirituall vnion iointly with all the perſons [<hi>He that cleaueth vnto God, is one ſpirit,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. Cor. 6.17.] ſo we haue a myſticall vnion peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly with Chriſt, as being made <hi>Man</hi> in nature, a <hi>Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> in office, and conſequently our <hi>Head.</hi> The ſecond, of the members amongſt themſelues. For <hi>we, being many, are one body in Chriſt, and euery one, one anothers members:</hi> Rom. 12.5. The members are not diuided in the body, nor the body from the head. The members are ioined with Chriſt by liuely faith; in themſelues by ardent loue. So there is a common life in them all; a mutuall ſenſe, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation in all things. The honour of Chriſt, by any, is our comfort: his diſhonour, by any, is our grief. The good, and proſperity of our brethren, is ours: their euill, and cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity alſo is ours. <hi>Who is weake</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul) and I am not weake? Who is offended, and I burne not?</hi> 2. Cor. 11.29.</p>
               <p>So much of the firſt benefite; to wit, <hi>viuification</hi> in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. The ſecond is, <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of ſoule &amp; body;—<hi>He hath <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> raiſed vs vp together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is the <hi>firſt</hi> &amp; the <hi>ſecond</hi> reſurrection. The firſt (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the <hi>Subiect</hi>) is of the ſoule, the 2. of the body. The firſt (in reſpect of <hi>Quality</hi>) is by grace, the ſecond to glory. The firſt (in reſpect of <hi>Time</hi>) is in this life, the 2. in the end of the world. So that the firſt is a <hi>praecurſor</hi> (aforeru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner) vnto the ſecond, &amp; <hi>prepareth</hi> a way thereunto. Finally; as there is a death <hi>in</hi> ſin, &amp; a death <hi>for</hi> ſin, ſo there is a double reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: the firſt <hi>à culpa,</hi> from ſin; the ſecond <hi>à poenae,</hi> from the puniſhment, which followeth thereupon. <hi>Anima corrupta in culpa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fecit quoque vt corpus corrumperetur in poenam;</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard:</hi> The ſoule was corrupted by ſinne, the body by the puniſhment thereof. So (ſaith he) <hi>mors mortem operata
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4291:14"/> eſt;</hi> one death wrought, or brought forth another: <hi>Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alis corporalem, culpabilis poenalem, voluntaria neceſſariam, &amp;c.</hi> The ſpirituall a corporall, the culpable a penall, the voluntary a neceſſary death.</p>
               <p>But now wee are raiſed vp from the one, and other. FIRST; we are raiſed vp from the death of the ſoule, by the ſpirit of illumination, and the ſpirit of ſanctification [two works, but one, and the ſame ſpirit] enlightning the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our vnderſtanding, and cleanſing the corruption of our hearts.</p>
               <p>This is the reſurrection, of which S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh; <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and holy is he, that hath part in the firſt reſurrection: for, on ſuch, death hath no power:</hi> Apocal. 20.6. For though death remaine in act, yet it is deſtroied in effect. Death died in Chriſt, and by Chriſt. <hi>O death, where is thy ſting? O graue, where is thy victory? The ſting of death is ſinne, and the ſtrength of ſinne is the law. But thanks be vnto God, who hath giuen vs the victory, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord:</hi> 1. Corinth. 15.55.56.57. So that, <hi>Non eſt malum in morte, niſi malum poſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem;</hi> There is no euill in the firſt death; all the euill, that is, is in the ſecond. Bleſſed then, indeed, &amp; holy is he, whoſe firſt life ſecureth him from the ſecond death.</p>
               <p>SECONDLY; how are we raiſed from the death of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, who are not yet dead therein? For the Apoſtle ſaith not; God <hi>will raiſe</hi> vs vp: but, God <hi>hath raiſed</hi> vs vp: as though it were not to come, but paſt.</p>
               <p>I anſwere <hi>firſt;</hi> that our corporall reſurrection is already paſt, in the preuiſion of God, to whom al things, which are to come, are actually preſent; and in the purpoſe of God, which changeth not. <hi>I am the Lord, and I change not,</hi> Mal. 3.6. So the Prophets, in the Law, and the Apoſtles, in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, do ſpeake of things, which are yet to come, as if they were already paſt; <hi>Propter certitudinem euentus:</hi> for the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the euent. Thus <hi>Eſay</hi> (the Euangelicall Prophet) ſaith expreſſely of Chriſt; <hi>He hath borne our infirmities: He was wounded for our tranſgreſſions: Hee was afflicted, &amp;c.</hi> Eſay 53. Theſe ſufferings of Chriſt were already paſt, in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4291:14"/> the eternall deſtination of the Father, but were yet to come, in the actuall oblation of himſelfe.</p>
               <p>J anſwer <hi>ſecondly;</hi> that wee are riſen in Chriſt, as in our Head; betwixt whom, and vs, there is an indiſſoluble con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion, and an inſeparable bond. For as there is a <hi>naturall</hi> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in Chriſt, of his body, and ſoule; an <hi>hypoſtaticall</hi> vnion of the humane nature with his diuine perſon; a <hi>ſacramental</hi> vnion of the bread with his body: ſo there is a <hi>myſticall</hi> vnion with vs: he being the Head, and we the members.</p>
               <p>Therefore, as in the ceremoniall Law, the <hi>firſt fruits</hi> being bleſſed, all the reſidue was bleſſed therein; ſo Chriſt (who was <hi>the firſt fruits of them, that ſlept,</hi> 1. Cor. 15.20.) being raiſed from the dead, we are alſo raiſed vp in him.</p>
               <p>And this is a ſingular comfort againſt the feare of death; though it bee the moſt terrible of all terrible things. Why ſhould we feare to die, who are already raiſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead? <hi>Our life is hid with God in Chriſt:</hi> Col. 3.3. Will he not keepe it ſafely, who bought it ſo dearely? Therefore <hi>I will lay mee downe, and ſleepe in peace; for thou, Lord, onely, makeſt mee to dwell in ſafety.</hi> Pſal. 4.8. With which comfortable ſentence, <hi>Gorgonia,</hi> the bleſſed ſiſter of <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> commended her ſoule into the hands of her Redeemer.</p>
               <p>Thus much of the ſecond benefit; to wit, <hi>Reſurrection of ſoule, and body.</hi> The third enſueth; namely, the <hi>Seſſion</hi> of both <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> in heauen. Before, we were quickned, then raiſed, now ſeated in heauen:—<hi>hee hath made vs ſit together in the heauenly places, in Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O happy life, to be ſo quickned! ô happy reſurrection, to be ſo raiſed! ô happy ſeſſion, to bee ſo placed! Firſt, hee hath made vs <hi>to ſit.</hi> This is a ſigne of our tranquillity, and reſt aboue, after much trouble, and motion heere, both in body, and ſoule. We are Pilgrimes vpon this earth, as all our fathers were. We are <hi>in via,</hi> in our way, to mooue; not <hi>in patria,</hi> in our countrey, to ſit downe. We may not ſtand ſtill; for that is reproued: <hi>Quid ſtatis hîc otioſi?</hi> Why ſtand you here idle? Mat. 20.6. We can not ſit; for that is reſerued vnto an other, and better, life; when <hi>many ſhall come from
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:4291:15"/> the Eaſt, and Weſt, and ſhall ſit downe with Abraham, Iſaac, and Iacob, in the kingdome of heauen:</hi> Mat. 8.11.</p>
               <p>SECONDLY then; he hath made vs ſit together <hi>in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly places:</hi> that is to ſay, in the heauen of bleſſed Angels, and Spirits; to whom God reuealeth himſelfe in the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of his glory. For though God filleth the heauen and earth, with his <hi>eſſence, preſence,</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> yet hee ſheweth not the like effects thereof in euery place. He is peculiarly in his elect by <hi>grace;</hi> peculiarly in heauen, by <hi>glory;</hi> which is <hi>the Chamber of preſence,</hi> wherein we ſhall ſee him, as he is, and behold him face to face. But what the qualities of theſe heauenly places are, or what are the ioies therein (as alſo, how the degrees of ioy are vnequall; ſince there are <hi>many manſions</hi> in heauen, Joh. 14.2. and that may be here impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the plurality; <hi>places</hi>) I neither can conceiue them, as they are, nor yet expreſſe what I conceiue thereof.</p>
               <p>I will therefore conclude this point, with that excellent ſpeech of <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> concerning the ioy of heauen; <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectò in me totum non intrabit, ſed ego in illud totus intrabo:</hi> truely it will not enter wholly into me, by knowledge, that I may apprehend it, but I ſhall enter wholly into it, by frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that I may enioy it, for euer, and euer.</p>
               <p>Now for the matter it ſelfe; <hi>We ſit in the heauenly places.</hi> How? Not by plenary poſſeſſion, but by the right of inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Not by perſonall fruition, but by aſſurance of faith. Finally, not in our ſelues, but in Chriſt our Head. So ſaith my text; he hath made vs ſit together in the heauenly places <hi>in Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> dreamed (Geneſ. 37.9. and it was a true dreame) that the <hi>Sunne,</hi> and the <hi>Moone</hi> (to wit, <hi>Iacob</hi> his father, and <hi>Rachel</hi> his mother) did reuerence vnto him, which yet ſhe neuer performed in her ſelfe (for <hi>Rachel</hi> died before, Geneſ. 35.19.) but in the perſon of <hi>Iacob,</hi> her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, when he came downe into the land of Egypt: ſo wee are already ſeated in the heauenly places, not in our ſelues, but in Chriſt our Head, who, as a <hi>Man,</hi> tooke our nature from his mother, and, as a <hi>Redeemer,</hi> vndertook our perſons
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:4291:15"/> with his Father: and ſo, what he hath receiued for vs, we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy in him. He being in heauen, we are in heauen alſo: he being aſcended, wee are aſcended thither with him. For though he deſcended alone, yet he is aſcended with vs.</p>
               <p>Therefore, whereas our Sauiour ſaith; <hi>No man aſcendeth into heauen, but he that deſcended from heauen, the Sonne of man, who is in heauen:</hi> Joh. 3.13. S. Bernard meditateth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, in this manner. <hi>Quid ergo nos?</hi> &amp;c. What then ſhall we doe? <hi>ſhall we deſpaire? No, but we will hope ſo much the more, and chiefely for this cauſe.</hi> Why? <hi>Licet enim</hi> SOLVS, <hi>ſed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectò</hi> TOTVS <hi>intrabit, &amp; os non comminuetur ex eo;</hi> for though hee, <hi>alone,</hi> ſhall enter into heauen, yet hee ſhall enter <hi>whole,</hi> and entire, and <hi>a bone of him ſhall not be broken.</hi> We are bone of his bone, and fleſh of his fleſh. He is the Head, and wee the members; the one is not found in the kingdome, without the other.</p>
               <p>And now my brethren, what doe wee vpon this <hi>earth?</hi> we, who are already ſeated in <hi>heauen?</hi> Why doe many men (nay all men, for <hi>all men ſeeke their owne, and not that, which is Ieſus Chriſts,</hi> Phil. 2.21.) ſo earneſtly ſeeke the firſt, and ſo careleſſely neglect the ſecond? The voluptuous man pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth his felicity in pleaſures, the ambitious man in honor, the couetous man in riches. <hi>Their end is damnation, their God is their belly, their glory is to their ſhame, they mind earthly things,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Paul,</hi> Philip. 3.19. He addeth; <hi>But our conuerſation is in heauen, from whence, alſo, we looke for the Sauiour, euen the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here, then, is a contemplation for euery ſoule. My Lord is aſcended into heauen; ſhall I neglect ſo good a place, as heauen, and ſo bleſſed company, as my IESVS? O where can I bee ill with him, or where can I be well without him? As he hath prepared a kingdome for me, ſo I will prepare my ſelfe for that kingdome, where J may reioice with him for euer, and no man ſhall take my ioy from me.</p>
               <p>Thus (beloued in Chriſt) we muſt aſcend, firſt in <hi>affection,</hi> as wee ſhall afterward in <hi>ſoule,</hi> and finally in <hi>body;</hi> that ſo, we may liue in him by <hi>grace,</hi> die in him with <hi>peace,</hi> &amp; raigne
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:4291:16"/> with him in <hi>glorie,</hi> for euer, and euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the <hi>Finall Cauſe</hi> of Gods benefits beſtowed vpon vs.</head>
               <p>I Am now come vnto the FIFTH, and laſt circumſtance of my text: to wit, the <hi>finall cauſe,</hi> or <hi>end</hi> of Gods benefits, beſtowed vpon vs, <hi>That he might ſhew, in the ages to come, the exceeding riches of his grace, through his kindneſſe toward vs in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My method ſhall be this: <hi>Firſt,</hi> I will make a briefe ſuruay of each particular in this verſe. <hi>Secondly,</hi> J will reflect vpon the generall doctrine, contained in the ſame.</p>
               <p>The particulars may be reduced vnto foure. The FIRST is, the <hi>End</hi> itſelfe,—<hi>that he might ſhew, in the ages to come, the exceeding riches of his grace.</hi> The SECOND is, the <hi>Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe</hi> of Gods affection, demonſtrated in this end— <hi>through his kindneſſe.</hi> The THIRD is, the <hi>perſons,</hi> or obiect, vnto which this kindneſſe is extended—<hi>vnto vs.</hi> The FOVRTH, and laſt is, the <hi>Meanes,</hi> by which God doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the ſame—<hi>in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the FIRST <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> (which is the end it ſelfe) you may obſerue; the <hi>Manner,</hi> how it is expreſſed—<hi>that hee might ſhew:</hi> the <hi>Time,</hi> when—<hi>in the ages to come:</hi> the <hi>Matter,</hi> which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed —<hi>the exceeding riches of his grace.</hi> Briefely of each.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Manner; <hi>That he might ſhew,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (ſaith the originall; and it is of greater force, then our tranſlation doth retaine) that he might ſhew it forth by demonſtration, and euidence: that ſo the world might ſee, admire, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud the bounty of his grace.</p>
               <p>Now there are two manner of waies, by which God doth ſhew himſelfe. <hi>Firſt,</hi> by his Word: which is full of maieſtie, and power. I meane not <hi>verbum Dominus,</hi> the Word which is God, but <hi>verbum Domini,</hi> the word of God. And of this our Apoſtle ſaith: <hi>The word of God is liuely, and mighty in operation,</hi> &amp;c. Hebru. 4.12. <hi>Secondly,</hi> by his Workes. By the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:4291:16"/> worke of <hi>Creation;</hi> ſo <hi>the heauens declare the glory of God, &amp; the firmament ſheweth the worke of his hands:</hi> Pſal. 19.1. By the worke of <hi>Conſeruation,</hi> in the ſingular adminiſtration of all his creatures, and admirable prouiſion for the ſame. But ſpecially in the worke of <hi>Redemption:</hi> in which God hath ſhewed his Iuſtice, his Power, and his Loue. His <hi>iuſtice,</hi> in the puniſhment of ſin: his <hi>power,</hi> in conquering the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Satan: his <hi>loue,</hi> in redeeming captiues.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The time—<hi>in the ages to come</hi> For <hi>hee hath made his wonderfull works to be had in remembrance:</hi> Pſal. 111.4. Hee ſuffereth them not to be obſcured in darkneſſe, nor buried in obliuion. Therfore he ſheweth them <hi>in the ages to come;</hi> not for a day, nor a yeare, but for eternity; to be conueigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from one generation vnto another. <hi>We will not hide them from our children, but, to the generation to come, we will ſhew the praiſes of the Lord, his power alſo, and his wonderfull works, that he hath done:</hi> Pſal. 78.4.</p>
               <p>Our <hi>tongue</hi> muſt be the trumpet of his praiſe; our <hi>heart,</hi> the regiſter of his works: a faithfull regiſter, to preſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for euer. Many men are moued at the benefits of God, for a time; their motion is quick in the beginning, but ſlow in the end: and yet it commeth ſoone to an end alſo. So it was with the people of Iſrael: <hi>They forgate his acts, and his wonderfull works, that he had ſhewed them.</hi> Pſal. 78.11.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Matter it ſelfe;—<hi>the exceeding riches of his grace.</hi> What this <hi>grace</hi> is, J told you <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 20.</note> before: to witte, the free, and voluntary fauour of God, exhibited vnto vs, in Ieſus Chriſt, his Sonne.</p>
               <p>Here it is accompanied with a paire of epithetes, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the nature, and quality therof. It is <hi>rich:</hi> yea, <hi>exceeding</hi> rich. A Sea of grace, which neuer can be exhauſted. An <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſſus,</hi> a bottomleſſe pit of grace, which neuer can bee ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Which as all men may admire, for the greatnes therof, ſo, ſpecially, a penitent ſinner may apply vnto himſelfe, for his own comfort. How can I doubt of remiſſion, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes of my ſinnes from him, who is ſo full of grace?</p>
               <p>If you require examples, for your better aſſurance, they
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:4291:17"/> are not wanting in this behalfe. I haue been an Idolater; ſo was <hi>Manaſſes.</hi> I haue been lewd of my body, ſo was <hi>Dauid.</hi> I haue been ouertaken with wine, ſo was <hi>Noah.</hi> I haue fled from God, ſo did <hi>Ionah.</hi> I haue denied my Lord, ſo did <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> I haue perſecuted him, in his members, ſo did <hi>Paul.</hi> I haue deſpoiled men of their goods, ſo did the penitent theefe, who was conuerted vpon the croſſe. Finally, I am full of iniquity, ſo was <hi>Mary Magdalen: peccatrix,</hi> the ſinful woman. All theſe obtained pardon by the grace of God, which they apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by faith. He wil not, therfore, reiect me, that embraced them. They could plead nothing but <hi>grace:</hi> and this, alſo, I can plead as well as they.</p>
               <p>Therefore, faint not vnder temptation: but take heede of the Diuels <hi>falſe glaſſe,</hi> wherein he repreſenteth thy ſinnes otherwiſe then they are indeed. For he hath two falſe glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; the <hi>firſt</hi> he bringeth, when he tempteth vs to ſinne: the <hi>ſecond,</hi> when he tempteth vs to deſpaire.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> when he tempteth vs to ſinne, he bringeth his falſe glaſſe, which maketh the ſin, and the puniſhment too, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare little in our eyes (as <hi>Lot</hi> ſaid of <hi>Zoar; is it not a little one, and my ſoule ſhall liue?</hi> Gen. 19.20.) yea, perhappes, none at all. God ſaid, by a direct affirmation, <hi>thou ſhalt not eate of the tree of knowledge; for, in the day, that thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt die the death:</hi> Gen. 2.17. The woman commeth in with a mincing heſitation; <hi>leſt perhaps you die:</hi> Geneſ. 3.3. The Diuell with a peremptorie negation; <hi>you ſhall not die at all.</hi> Such goodly creatures, as you, die for an apple, or ſome fruit of litle value? No, ſaith he, <hi>you ſhall not die.</hi> But Gods word was the truer; for Adam did <hi>die the death.</hi> The leſſer the precept was, in reſpect of the matter, and thing it ſelfe, the greater was the ſinne, in reſpect of the diſobedience, &amp; contempt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> when we haue committed a ſinne, vpon his ſuggeſtion, &amp; our conſent, then he bringeth another falſe glaſſe, wherein he maketh our ſinne appeare ſo great, that God himſelfe is not great enough to forgiue the ſame. <hi>My ſinne is greater</hi> (ſaith deſperate <hi>Cain,</hi> Gen. 4.13.) <hi>then that it
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:4291:17"/> can be forgiuen</hi> But here, <hi>Cain,</hi> I dare giue thee the lie (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy Diuell, who is the <hi>father of lies,</hi> Ioh. 8.44) for <hi>no ſin is ſo great, but that God can</hi> (ſuch is his power) <hi>and will</hi> (ſuch is his goodnes) <hi>forgiue the ſame.</hi> Js it not, ſimply, the ſinne committed, but our impenitencie, added vnto ſinne, which maketh it irremiſſible in euent, that is, otherwiſe, remiſſible in it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>In all ſuch temptations, therefore, which doe, or may, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault vs, it is good to haue S. <hi>Peters</hi> counſell (1. Pet. 5.9.) euermore ſet before our eyes; <hi>Reſiſtite,</hi> reſiſt him. How muſt we reſiſt him? <hi>Fortes,</hi> being ſtrong and ſtedfaſt. Wherein muſt we be ſtrong, and ſtedfaſt? <hi>In fide,</hi> in faith; that it may apprehend the grace of God. For if I ſinne, he hath <hi>grace.</hi> If my ſinnes be great, there is the <hi>riches</hi> of his grace. If my ſins be in number, as the ſands of the ſea (and were euery ſand a milſtone) there is the <hi>exceeding</hi> riches of his grace. <hi>Excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> aboue all my ſinnes.</p>
               <p>For if it be true (and it is moſt true) that the <hi>mercy of God is ouer</hi> [or <hi>aboue] all his works;</hi> Pſal 145.9. is it not ouer, &amp; aboue all, my works alſo? Howſoeuer his be good, and <hi>very good</hi> (Geneſ. 1.31.) mine euill, and very euill, that is not the point: he will not haue his grace, and mercy, to bee excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by my ſinnes. <hi>Plus poteſt dimittere, quàm ego committere;</hi> he can remit more vnto me, then I can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit againſt him. And ſo much of the firſt.</p>
               <p>The SECOND particular is, the <hi>Tenderneſſe</hi> of Gods af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection —<hi>through his kindnes.</hi> Sweete is the name, and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſweeter is the thing. <hi>Thy louing kindneſſe is better, then life: therefore my lips ſhall praiſe thee:</hi> Pſal. 63.3. Let mee repeate it once againe; O that I might dwell, for euer, in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of this heauenly, and diuine ſentence: <hi>Thy lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing kindnes is better, then life: therefore my lippes ſhall praiſe thee.</hi> O Lord thou art without paſſion, but not without compaſſion. <hi>The Lord is mercifull, and righteous, and our God is full of compaſſion.</hi> Pſal. 116.5.</p>
               <p>In regard whereof, it is, that, in the holy Scriptures, wee finde him compared, ſometimes to a <hi>Friend,</hi> ſomtimes to a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:4291:18"/> 
                  <hi>Father,</hi> ſomtimes to a <hi>Mother,</hi> ſometimes to an <hi>Husband:</hi> that ſo, by theſe familiar ſpeeches, we might aſpire vnto ſome ſenſe, &amp; knowledge, of his indulgent, and compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate nature.</p>
               <p>But ſince, before, his other attributes were attended with certaine epithetes, to amplifie the dignity thereof (as <hi>rich</hi> Mercy, <hi>great</hi> Loue, <hi>exceeding</hi> Grace) is there none here, for his <hi>Kindneſſe,</hi> which is the ſpring, and fountaine, whence all the reſt proceed? It needed not: the cauſe is ſufficiently commended by the effects. Howbeit, wee may aſſume certaine epithetes from ſome other paſſages of Scripture, as in that place which I mentioned before: <hi>Thy louing kindneſſe:</hi> and Ionah. 42. <hi>Thou art of great kindneſſe.</hi> Compound theſe ſimples, and you ſhall haue, <hi>great louing</hi> kindneſſe in God.</p>
               <p>This, this is it, which, aboue all other things, doth winne our hearts vnto God, if not in piety, yet in good nature. For what doth more ſingularly affect vs, then the <hi>kindneſſe,</hi> and ſweet diſpoſition of a Friend, or what can oblige vs more, in the ſtraiteſt bonds of loue? <hi>Woe is me</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) for thee, my brother Ionathan.</hi> Why? <hi>Very kind haſt thou beene vnto me:</hi> 2. Sam. 1.26. But the <hi>kindneſſe</hi> of God doth as far ſurpaſſe the <hi>kindnes</hi> of man, as GOD excelleth MAN: that is to ſay, <hi>infinitely,</hi> beyond all proportion, and without any meaſure. And ſo much of the ſecond.</p>
               <p>The THIRD particular is, the <hi>Obiect</hi> of this kindneſſe: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>Vs</hi>—his kindneſſe <hi>toward vs.</hi> Not toward the <hi>good Angels;</hi> they were in the poſſibility, not in the act of ſinne. So they needed not redemption from ſinne, but confirmation in grace: and conſequently, they needed not the kindnes of God; at the leaſt, not in this ſenſe, whereof I now intreat. Not toward the <hi>bad Angels:</hi> whom God left iuſtly vnto ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duration, in their pride againſt him, and malice againſt vs. Not toward <hi>vnreaſonable creatures:</hi> they were not capable thereof. But toward vs. <hi>Men,</hi> who needed it, and fell by the ſuggeſtion of others, and were capable of this kindneſſe: but had no means to redeem our ſelues from the power of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:4291:18"/> Satan, who held vs in the captiuity of ſinne and death.</p>
               <p>Here, then, was a fit caſe, wherein the kindneſſe of God might fully, and excellently, declare it ſelfe. And truly God did thus declare his <hi>kindneſſe,</hi> but yet in <hi>iustice</hi> alſo. S. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> deſcribeth it ingenuouſly, and bringeth in the Sonne of God, ſpeaking in this manner. Behold how, for my ſake, my Father doth loſe his creatures. The Angels affected my <hi>highneſſe,</hi> but preſently he ſtrooke them with an incureable wound. Then, Man affected my <hi>knowledge:</hi> vpon him alſo my Father had no pitie, neither did his eye ſpare him. Hath be, then, care of oxen? He made onely two noble creatures, partakers of reaſon, and capeable of felicity; to wit, <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Men:</hi> but loe, for mee he hath deſtroied all Men, and many Angels. Now, therefore, that men may know, how I loue the Father: <hi>recipiat per me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> quos quodammodò, propter me, amiſiſſe videtur:</hi> Let him receiue them againe, by my meanes, whom he ſeemeth, in a maner, to haue loſt for my ſake.</p>
               <p>So the Sonne of God reſtored vs againe vnto his Father, by iuſtice, paying the iuſt price, and full ranſom of our ſins. <hi>Thou haſt redeemed vs vnto God by thy bloud.</hi> Apocal. 5.9. By the expenſe of his temporall, he hath purchaſed our eternal life. That we might haue it, as a gift, he hath giuen himſelfe for vs. Therefore wel ſaith the Apoſtle here in my text; that the kindnes of God towards <hi>vs,</hi> was in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And this <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> is the FOVRTH particular in this verſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, of the words: ſecondly, of the matter. In the words there are many obſeruable points (but I may not be copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous therein) as namely, <hi>Ieſus</hi> is a name of ſaluation, <hi>Chriſt</hi> a name of vnction. The firſt importeth his <hi>Diuinity:</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, his <hi>Humanity.</hi> The firſt is taken from the Hebrewes, to ſhew, that he is a Sauiour of the <hi>Iewes:</hi> the ſecond from the Greeks, to ſhew, that he is a Sauiour alſo of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> For though he was ſent onely to the Iewes, yet hee was not ſent only <hi>for</hi> the Iewes. He was ſent to them onely, <hi>pradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catione verbi,</hi> to call them to repentance, by preaching the word of life: he was ſent for vs all, <hi>ſolutione presij,</hi> to redeeme
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:4291:19"/> vs from ſin, by paying the ranſome thereof, in the effuſion of his bloud. Both names are here ioyned together: for as each people (<hi>Iew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi>) hath the ſame Sauiour, and are both vnited in him, ſo each hath right, equally, in the ſame benefits, which hee hath purchaſed for both. And <hi>though obſtinacy become to Iſrael,</hi> yet that is, <hi>vntill the fulneſſe of the Gentiles become in: and ſo all Iſrael ſhall be ſaued:</hi> Rom. 11.25, 26. <hi>He [the Iew] that was firſt, ſhal be laſt:</hi> but yet he ſhal be called in, and before, the end.</p>
               <p>So much of the words; now to the matter. <hi>No man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto the Fahher but by the Sonne:</hi> Iohn 14.6. No bleſſing commeth from the Father alſo, but by the Sonne; and, <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer we aske of the Father, in his name, he will giue it vnto vs:</hi> Ioh. 15.16. He is the ladder of <hi>Iacob</hi> Gen. 28.12.) reaching, <hi>from the earth</hi> [in his Humanity] <hi>to heauen</hi> [in his Diuinity] that ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by him, we may aſcend from our earthly habitations below, vnto the heauenly places aboue. Therefore ſaith our Apoſtle: <hi>Bleſſed bee God, euen the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which hath bleſſed vs with all ſpirituall bleſſings in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly things, in Chriſt.</hi> As namely, the bleſſings of <hi>Election, Filiation, Redemption:</hi> in which (as in the reſt) the Father vſeth the Sonne; howbeit, not as an inſtrumentall meanes, but a cooperatiue cauſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Whatſoeuer things he Father doth, the ſame doth the Sonne alſo:</hi> Ioh. 5.19. Yea the ſame doth the holy Ghoſt alſo. For though the internall actions of God be proper vnto each perſon by himſelfe, yet the externall are common vnto them all.</p>
               <p>To the point. The <hi>Firſt</hi> bleſſing was, of Election. The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther choſe vs in his Son <hi>He choſe vs in him, before the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the world:</hi> Epheſ. 1.4. The <hi>Second</hi> bleſſing was, of Filiation. The Father hath adopted vs in his Sonne: ſo that he was a Son by <hi>nature,</hi> we by <hi>grace</hi> in him; he by <hi>generation,</hi> we by <hi>adoption</hi> in him. The Father hath many ſons in one Sonne. <hi>He</hi> [the Father] <hi>hath predeſtinated vs to be adopted, through Ieſus Chriſt, vnto himſelfe, according to the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his will:</hi> Epheſ. 1.5. The <hi>third</hi> bleſſing was, of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. <hi>God</hi> [the Father] <hi>was in Chriſt, recontiling the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:4291:19"/> world vnto himſelfe:</hi> 2. Cor. 5 19. Jn regard whereof, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpake from heauen, ſaying: <hi>This is my beloued Sonne, in whom I am well pleaſed.</hi> Mat. 3.17. <hi>In</hi> him, and <hi>with</hi> vs. For if the ſacrifice, offered vp by <hi>Noah</hi> (which was but of birds, and beaſts) had ſuch efficacic, and vertue, that <hi>God ſmelled a ſauour of reſt</hi> therein (Gen. 8 21.) much more did he ſmell <hi>a ſauour of reſt</hi> in the bloudy ſacrifice of his onely begotten and dearely beloued Sonne. For behold, here is a greater then <hi>Noah,</hi> and a greater ſacrifice then his. His ſacrifice yeelded <hi>a ſauour of reſt</hi> vnto God, by acceptation, this by deſert: his by the mercy of the Father, this by merit of the Sonne.</p>
               <p>Now ſince the whole ſum and parts of our ſaluation, are thus comprehended in our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, we muſt not deriue any parcell thereof (directly, nor indirectly; poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely, nor conſequently) vnto any other (Man, or Angell) but <hi>looke alwaies vnto him, the author, and finiſher of our faith:</hi> Heb. 12.2. If we ſeeke ſaluation, it is in his name: if any gifts of the ſpirit, they are in his vnction: if fortitude, it is in his dominion: if purity, it is in his conception: if indulgence, it is in his natiuity: if redemption, it is in his paſſion: if abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, it is in his condemnation: if remiſſion of the curſe, it is in his croſſe: if ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it is in his ſacrifice: if purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is in his bloud: if mortificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it is in his graue: if new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life, it is in his reſurrection: if immortality, it is in his reuiuing: if inheritance of heauen, it is in his entrance thither: if ſafety, it is in his kingdome: if ſecure expectation of the iudgement to come, it is in the power of iudging, which the Father hath committed vnto him. <hi>For the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther iudgeth no man, but hath committed all iudgement vnto the Sonne:</hi> Iohn 5.22, Why? <hi>Becauſe all men ſhould honour the Son, as they honour the Father.</hi> Let vs honour him therefore, and the Father, aſcribing <hi>praiſe, and honour, and glory, and power vnto him, that sitteth vpon the throne, and vnto the Lambe, for euermore. Amen</hi> Apoc. 5.13.</p>
               <p>Thus much of the foure particulars, in the laſt verſe of my texe. It remaineth now, that (according to my <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 30.</note> deſigne) I
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:4291:20"/> reflect vpon the generall doctrine, which is contained in the ſame: and ſo, by it, I will make a tranſition vnto my own particular caſe. The conſideration whereof hath treated with me to make ſpeciall choice of this text, in regard of ſundry markeable effects of Gods <hi>mercy, loue,</hi> and <hi>grace,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me; which as I feele, comfortably, in my ſelfe, ſo I would impart, willingly, vnto you.</p>
               <p>The generall doctrine (ſtreaming out of the premiſes) concerneth the glory of God, which he ſeeketh and obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in all his works. In our glory, he aduanceth his owne; as our Apoſtle ſaith: <hi>He declareth the riches of his glory, vpon the veſſels of mercy, which hee hath prepared vnto glory.</hi> Rom. 9.22.</p>
               <p>Here his glory is ſhewed in his mercy, which, ſometimes, he ſheweth in his iuſtice alſo: but with different effect to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vs. For then he is glorified <hi>in</hi> vs, not <hi>of</hi> vs: he getteth glory, we giue it not: we are <hi>paſſiue</hi> in the one, <hi>actiue</hi> in the other.</p>
               <p>Firſt, he is glorified <hi>in</hi> vs: that is to ſay, in our deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by his iuſtice. <hi>I will get me honour</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>vpon Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh, and vpon all his hoſt.</hi> Exod. 14.4. <hi>Glorificabor in Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> (as the vulgar hath it: and neerer vnto the originall) I wil be glorified <hi>in</hi> Pharaoh: that is, my honour, and glory ſhall be declared, eminently, in his ruine, and fall. <hi>Fiet vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas Dei, aut à nobis, aut de nobis:</hi> the will of God ſhall be done <hi>vpon vs,</hi> if not <hi>by</hi> vs; as here you may ſee in the lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſubmerſion, &amp; ſubuerſion, of this puiſſant and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty King.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he is glorified <hi>of</hi> vs: that is to ſay, in our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by his mercy. <hi>Call vpon me</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>in the day of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſo I will deliuer thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie me.</hi> Pſal. 50.15. Here is a good harmony, &amp; concord: God deliuereth man: Man glorifieth God: God is honoured, and man is ſaued.</p>
               <p>Both theſe glorifications are ioyned together by <hi>Moſes,</hi> after he had ſeene the confuſion of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and the deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Iſrael. <hi>I will ſing vnto the Lord, for he hath triumphed gloriouſly: the horſe, and him, that rode vpon him, hath hee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:4291:20"/> in the ſea.</hi> There is the <hi>Firſt.</hi> Behold the <hi>Second.</hi> It followeth. <hi>The Lord is my ſtrength, and my praiſe, and he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come my ſaluation. He is my God, and I will prepare him a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle: he is my Fathers God, and I will exalt him:</hi> Exodus 15.1.2.</p>
               <p>This latter glorification is that, which here appertaineth vnto vs. GOD hath ſhewed his glory, not in iudgement, but in <hi>mercy,</hi> in <hi>loue,</hi> and in <hi>grace:</hi> which he hath plentifully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended towards vs, <hi>giuing vs life,</hi> when we were dead, <hi>raiſing vs vp,</hi> when we were fallen, <hi>placing vs in heauen,</hi> when we were at the gates of hell.</p>
               <p>Now, for as much as God doth ſo highly honour vs in this world, and will honour vs more in the world to come: what ſhall we do, but honour him alſo in this world, whom we ſhall, likewiſe, honour in the next? The end of our <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> requireth it. All things were made for the vſe of man; man for the ſeruice of God. The end of our <hi>Preſeruation</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth it. We liue by the benefits of God: we muſt liue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to his honour. The end of our redemption requireth it. For what priſoner will not exalt, and magnifie a King, that giueth him his naturall life, when he was ciuilly dead, and, by his mercy, freeth him from the ſword of iuſtice? But as our eſtate was more miſerable, then the condition of any priſoner, ſo God hath dealt more roially with vs, then that any mortall Prince is able to performe the like. Hee hath freed vs from the infernall priſon of hell, from the terrible iawes of Satan; he hath reſtored vs vnto <hi>the glorious libertie of the ſons of God:</hi> yea more then this, he hath but one king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and but one Sonne, yet, behold he hath made vs <hi>co heires with him</hi> therein: Rom. 8.17. What, then, could he doe for vs, and he hath not done it?</p>
               <p>And now finally, leſt we ſhould pretend a difficultie in this ſeruice, ſee the facility thereof. God hath <hi>ſhewed</hi> his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, let vs, alſo, <hi>ſhew</hi> them: and this is the ſeruice, which he requireth at our hands.</p>
               <p>Howbeit, there is a great diſparity betwixt his, and our <hi>ſhewing</hi> the ſame. He ſheweth his benefits by <hi>donation,</hi> wee
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:4291:21"/> by <hi>declaration:</hi> his is <hi>reall,</hi> ours <hi>verball.</hi> He ſheweth his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits; and we haue an acceſſion, or increaſe of our happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereby. We ſhew them; but the infinite ſea of his happineſſe (which dependeth not vpon his creatures) is not increaſed by the riuers of praiſes, which are poured foorth of our lips. In a word, he ſheweth, and it is his <hi>voluntary li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitie</hi> toward vs; we ſhew, and it is our <hi>neceſſary duty</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him.</p>
               <p>An eaſie, and a iuſt ſeruice. Therefore ſaith the Angel vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Tobit,</hi> and his ſonne: <hi>Praiſe God, and confeſſe him, and giue him the glory, and praiſe him for the things that he hath done vnto you, before all them that liue. It is good to praiſe God, and to exalt his name, and to ſhew forth his euident works with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor: therefore be not weary to confeſſe him. It is good to keep cloſe the ſecrets of a</hi> KING, <hi>but it is honourable to reueale the works of</hi> GOD: Tobit 12.6.7.</p>
               <p>His benefits, then, that are priuate vnto our ſelues, we muſt make publike vnto others. He was an vnfaithful, and an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſeruant alſo, who, receiuing a talent from his maſter, <hi>hid it in the earth</hi> (Mat. 25.25.) and did not imploy it to his aduantage. Likewiſe he is an vngrateful perſon, who recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth a bleſſing from God, and concealeth it in his boſome.</p>
               <p>Let euery man, therefore, recount with himſelfe the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits which God hath beſtowed vpon him. Be they inward, or outward; ſpirituall, or temporall; concerning this life, or the life to come: ſhew them, declare them; firſt in <hi>word,</hi> then in <hi>worke,</hi> that men may <hi>glorifie your Father which is in heauen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd that I may induce you vnto this acceptable ſeruice, not onely by my ſpeech, but by my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample alſo; Fathers, and Brethren, Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, right Worſhipful, and dearely beloued in Ieſus Chriſt our Lord: I preſent my ſelfe here this day, as
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:4291:21"/>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.9.</note>
                  <hi>aſpectacle vnto the world, and to Angels, and to men;</hi> though with ſome regret, and reluctation of the fleſh, yet with great comfort, and exultation of the ſpirit.<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark.</hi> 14.38.</note> 
                  <hi>The ſpirit, indeed, is ready, but the fleſh is weake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Come,</hi> therefore, <hi>and hearken all ye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that feare the Lord, and I will tell you, what he hath done to my ſoule.</hi> So doth <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> inuite his auditors, and ſo doe I inuite mine. <hi>Come.</hi> Who? <hi>All ye that feare the Lord.</hi> For they, that feare him not, are as vnfit to heare this ſeruice performed by an other, as they are vnable to performe it themſelues. But your religious concourſe vnto this place, your diligent attention of my ſpeech, your reuerent eſtimation of Gods word, your zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous profeſſion of his truth, all theſe aſſure me, that you are ſuch indeed, as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh of in this place; <hi>you feare the Lord.</hi> Therefore <hi>come, and hearken al you, and I will tell you, what he hath done to my ſoule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, yet, before I tel you, what God hath done vnto me, I muſt tell you, what I haue done vnto him; for this is the trueſt methode to illuſtrate his gratious fauours. <hi>Vide, quid tibi debeatur</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine) &amp; quid tibi dederit, qui gratis dedit;</hi> ſee, <hi>firſt,</hi> what is due vnto thee: <hi>ſecondly,</hi> what God hath done for thee; <hi>then,</hi> how freely hee hath done the ſame.</p>
               <p>Firſt therefore, becauſe we giue glory vnto God, by the humble confeſſion of our ſins (ſo ſaid <hi>Ioſuah</hi> vnto <hi>Achan;</hi> 
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 7.19.</note>
                  <hi>My ſonne, I beſeech thee giue glory vnto the Lord God of Iſrael, and make confeſſion vnto him, and ſhew mee now, what thou haſt done</hi>) I confeſſe vnto almighty GOD, in the face of his CHVRCH, that, in part, I haue denied my Lord with <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp; betrayed him with <hi>Iudas,</hi> and crucified him with the <hi>Iewes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A grieuous ſinne, and a great puniſhment too; <hi>malum culpae</hi> turned into malum <hi>poenae,</hi> when one ſinne is made the puniſhment of another; the iuſtice of God ſhining in the iniuſtice of man. Thus my vngratitude for his benefits, my negligence in his ſeruice, my affectation of vaine glory, my impatience at calamities, and my other ſinnes, were puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:4291:22"/> with the ſinne of <hi>Apoſtaſie,</hi> and defection from the truth, euen from the ſincerity of the Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt So that I proceeded from one fal vnto an other; firſt in my <hi>Will,</hi> &amp; then in my <hi>vnderſtanding;</hi> firſt, <hi>à bono,</hi> and then <hi>à verò;</hi> firſt in <hi>manners,</hi> and then in <hi>faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here now, peraduenture, ſome will ſay vnto me, as <hi>Michal</hi> vnto <hi>Dauid,</hi> when ſhe deſpiſed him in her heart; <note n="e" place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.20.21.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou haſt vncouered thy ſelfe, as a foole this day.</hi> But vnto them I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, as <hi>Dauid</hi> vnto <hi>Michal: It was before the Lord and I will, yet, be more vile then thus, and will be low in mine own ſight.</hi> Let the proud <hi>Phariſee</hi> boaſt; <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 8.11.13.</note> 
                  <hi>I am not, as other men.</hi> But I will pray, with the deiected <hi>Publican; O God bee mercifull vnto me, a ſinner.</hi> Finally, I ſay with <note n="g" place="margin">Confeſſ. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> S. <hi>Auguſtine; Irrideat me arrogantes, &amp; nondum ſalubriter proſtrats, &amp; eliſi, à te, Deus meus; ego autem confitear tibi dedecora mea in laude tuâ:</hi> Let them, who were neuer broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; humbled vnder thy hand, let them, I ſay, deride me: but, as for me, ô Lord, let me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe my diſhonour in thy praiſe, my ſhame to thy glory.</p>
               <p>To proceed, then, in that, which I haue begun. My fall was great, and dangerous, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering <hi>Vnde, &amp; Quò,</hi> whence, and whither I fell: to wit, from the ſimplicity of that truth, which is in Chriſt, into a ſinke of ſuperſtition, idolatrie, and error: euen the confuſion of the ſpirituall <hi>Babylon</hi> it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>And yet there are two things, principally, aboue the reſt, wherein my heart neuer was, nor could be, farther eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, then by an implicite, inuolued, obſcure faith of the Church. Thoſe are JMAGES, and INDVLGENCES (affix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto dead ſtatues, vnto our Ladies ſlippers, and the like trumperie) with <hi>holy graines, agnus De<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> and ſundry like profanations, <hi>Babylonian</hi> 
                  <note n="h" place="margin">See <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal.</hi> 18.3.11.23.</note> merchandiſe, the dregges of the meretricious, inchanting cup, wherewith <hi>the inhabitants of the earth haue been drunken.</hi> Apocal. 17.2.</p>
               <p>You ſee the <hi>Matter,</hi> wherein I fell, and how that doth augment the enormity of my fall. See now farther, how it was yet more capitall, in reſpect of my <hi>Perſon;</hi> I meane, in reference vnto my function, and office, in the Church of Chriſt; which, in it ſelfe, was very ſpectable, yea honourable
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:4291:22"/> alſo, howſoeuer my deſerts were greatly euill, or meanely good, therein. <hi>Fac opus Euangeliſtae, miniſterium tuum imple,</hi> ſaith S. <note n="i." place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> vnto <hi>Timothy;</hi> Doe the worke of an euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt, fulfill thy miniſtery; by frequent labour, by ſound do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, by innocent, and vnoffenſiue life: not <hi>faſhioning thy ſelfe,</hi> in the leuity of thy deportment, in the ſeruice of thy appetite, in vnſeemely, and prodigious apparel], <hi>according to this preſent world.</hi> In which things as I cannot excuſe my ſelfe, ſo I wiſh, that I, alone, were to be accuſed in the ſame. Theſe are vices, ignoble, ſcandalous vices, vnto which I de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nounce immortall war, as in all men ſo, principally, in thoſe, who are of my condition and place.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, you will enquire of the <hi>Manner,</hi> and <hi>occaſion</hi> of my fall; which I will relate vnto you freely, and ſincerely, in the candor, and ſimplicity of my heart.</p>
               <p>It is true, that, ſometime before my fall, or any propen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vnto the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, ſundry difficulties did inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe me, on euery ſide; <hi>degnè pro meritis, durè pro viribus;</hi> as S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeaketh: iuſtly for my deſerts, ô Lord, but yet hardly for my ſtrength. And though theſe euils did breed a <hi>naturall alteration</hi> in mee (euen in my ſpirits, and in my ſtrength: ſo that I ſaid vnaduiſedly in my ſelfe: <hi>it is better for me to die, then to liue:</hi> Ionah 4.8.) yet all this while, I ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered no <hi>morall alteration:</hi> theſe things did not preuaile in me vnto any mutation of my faith, either by an inward, or by an outward change.</p>
               <p>Howbeit I denie not, but that (the inferiour parts of my ſoule rebelling againſt the ſuperiour) my earthly, darke affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions might, and did, interpoſe themſelues to eclipſe the light of my vnderſtanding; the edge whereof was now ſo dulled, and ſo abated, that it gaue place more eaſily vnto er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, then perhaps, otherwiſe it would haue done.</p>
               <p>See, therefore, the euent. I found, but ſought not, an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of diſpute with ſome ingenious, and learned Papiſts, whoſe names, and qualities, I may not, I will not expreſſe. Neither they, in particular, nor any other, amongſt them, ſhall euer ſay of me, iuſtly, that I had ſo little wit, or ſo il na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:4291:23"/> as to procure them hurt, who in act, or at the leaſt, in their intention, were kind, and beneficiall vnto me.</p>
               <p>In this diſpute, then (which was, concerning <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and <hi>praier for the dead</hi>) it ſo fell out, by the force of obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which they made vnto me, and I made vnto my ſelfe, out of ſundry authors, old, and new, of the one ſide, and the other, that my vnderſtanding (vpon ſome defect) was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced, rather then my conſcience perſwaded, in this point.</p>
               <p>You <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſee the beginning of my euill. <note n="k." place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.8.</note> 
                  <hi>All this was but the beginning of ſorrowes.</hi> You ſhall heare the progreſſion, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.</p>
               <p>When I was thus heated in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> I began to waxe cold in the affection of my former faith; and the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> I conceiued (but miſconceiued; and this was the SE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COND motiue of my change) that mine own Maſters, and Teachers (ſome principall Diuines in this Church) had led me into error, by their writings. Wherein if I found a <hi>m<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ate,</hi> I made it a <hi>beame;</hi> and, if I found nothing, I made ſomething: as Caeſar ſpake, ſometimes, of his way, and paſſage; <hi>Inueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, aut faciam,</hi> I ſhall finde one made to my hands, or elſe I will make one my ſelfe: ſo it was with me, in that vnfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and diſaſtrous time; which I can not remember, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out griefe, nor recount without teares.</p>
               <p>The THIRD <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> occaſion, or motiue, of my change, was the controuerſie of <hi>Vocation,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſticall function;</hi> which are <note n="l" place="margin">See <hi>Doct. Field,</hi> of the Church lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>eſſentiall vnto the being of a Church, and inſeparable from the ſame.</hi> Here, then, many defects were pretended ſtrongly, and with ſuch probability (but by miſpriſion in them, and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance in me) that our <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ocation,</hi> ſeemed profane, our <hi>Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> ſacrilegious, in mine eies.</p>
               <p>The FOVRTH, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and laſt (for I need remember no more vnto you) was concerning the CHVRCH it ſelfe; which, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the higheſt ſphere in the great world of theological con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies, at this day, containeth all the teſt in her wombe, and embraceth them within her armes.</p>
               <p>Theſe were the foure points, which (originally, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally) did worke with my <hi>Vnderſtanding</hi> (and ſuperiour
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:4291:23"/> part of my ſoule) to ouercome me, while my traiterous <hi>Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> (the inferiour part) ſolicited me to yeeld. For it is true, that the affections of a man are, vnto his Vnderſtanding, as <note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Judg.</hi> 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Delilah</hi> was vnto <hi>Sampſon:</hi> firſt, alluring it to betray its owne ſtrength; then, deliuering it ouer vnto falſehood, and errour (as ſhe, hauing beguiled <hi>Sampſon,</hi> deliuered him into the hands of the <hi>Philiſtims</hi>) which, hauing gotten a conqueſt, wil make a triumph alſo. O beware of this <hi>Eue,</hi> which, lying in your owne boſome, will ſeduce you; take heede of your <hi>affections,</hi> which alwaies contriue ſome treaſonable plot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your <hi>vnderstanding.</hi> Let the affections be a ſeruant, as <hi>Hagar;</hi> your reaſon free, as <hi>Sarah:</hi> if they contend, <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.10.</note> 
                  <hi>caſt out the bondwoman, and her ſonne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus I, (miſerable, diſtreſſed J) like a <note n="o" place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 6.</note> blinde <hi>Aramite,</hi> was conducted into Idolatrous <hi>Samaria,</hi> and neuer thought my ſelfe ſecure, til I was in my greateſt danger. I fled my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue countrey (<note n="p" place="margin">Senec. in Med.</note>
                  <hi>Fugimus läſon, fugimus; hoc non eſt nouum;</hi> it is no newes to heare of ſuch flying; many fled before me: I wiſh that neuer any fly after me) to go into a forraine land. But here I may demand of my ſelfe, as <hi>Eliah,</hi> ſometime, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of <hi>Ahaziahs</hi> ſeruants; <note n="q" place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 1.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Was it not, becauſe there was no God in Iſrael</hi> [England] <hi>that I went to enquire of Baal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebub, the God of Ekron</hi> [Rome] <hi>concerning my eſtate?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſpake of <hi>Philiſtims</hi> before; but now I was in the hands of <hi>Philiſtims</hi> indeed: for whom J had neuer ground (as <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Judg.</hi> 16.21.</note>
                  <hi>Sampſon</hi> did) vnleſſe I (as <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Sampſon</hi> was) had beene firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of mine eies.</p>
               <p>Now I began to be in trauel with an vnhappy birth, which I had conceiued before; I meane, that <hi>Purgatory</hi>-diſcourſe, which, in the heate of my <hi>ignis fatuus,</hi> and popiſh zeale, I ſent back into my countrey; as you know: I wiſh you knew not. But as it had no right to inherit in this kingdome, ſince it was borne in tranſmarine, and forraine parts; ſo it was vnfit to be naturalized heere, which came from ſo vnnaturall a Parent.</p>
               <p>Howbeit, I meaſure not my fact by the euent: my intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was not the leſſe euill, becauſe the effect was not more
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:4291:24"/> euill. No? I ſpared none: not the truth of God; much leſſe them, by whom it was maintained in this Land.</p>
               <p>In which number there are two, whom I ſcandalized (as vniuſtly, ſo chiefly) aboue the reſt. The one is, the learned, and venerable Deane of <hi>Wincheſter;</hi> of whoſe knowledge, and charity, I haue had ſo much experience, that, whether he be <hi>melior,</hi> or <hi>doctior,</hi> a better man, or a more learned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, I can not eaſily reſolue. Only I can reſolue with <hi>Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca;</hi> that, of theſe two commendations, <hi>ô virum doctum,</hi> and, <hi>ô virum bonum,</hi> the latter doth excell the firſt. The other is, the like learned, and venerable Deane of <hi>Gloceſter;</hi> of whom J may proteſt vnfaignedly; <note n="ſ" place="margin">Hieron. ad Auguſtin. inter Epiſt. Aug. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Coepi illum antè amare, quam nôſſe,</hi> I began to loue him, before I began to know him: in regard of <hi>that, which I haue heard, and which I haue ſeene with mine eies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe I ſay, are the men, whom J ſcandalized (as vniuſtly, ſo chiefly) aboue the reſt. And ſo I fell, expreſſely, into <note n="t" place="margin">Vide. epiſt. Aug. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>S. Hieromes</hi> cenſure; <hi>Puerilis eſt iactantia, accuſando illuſtres viros, ſuo nomini famam quaerere,</hi> it is a childiſh vaunt in any, by accuſing illuſtrious men, to ſeeke his owne exiſtimation, and fame. But they haue taken ſome amends of me, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their will; there are others, vnto whom J would make amends, according to my power. I will name one, in ſteed of all; the moſt Reuerend Archbiſhop of <hi>Yorke;</hi> a faire iewel, a rich diamond of this Church.</p>
               <p>Vpon him this euill aſperſion was long ſince caſt by <hi>Edm. Campian,</hi> and lately renewed by me; to wit, that his Grace being, ſometime, familiarly demanded by <hi>Campian</hi> in this manner; <hi>Whether hee, that imploied himſelfe daily in peruſing the ancient Fathers, could, indeed, be of that opinion himſelfe, which he perſwaded vnto others; did anſwer thereupon: That truely he could not, if he ſhould read the Fathers and beleeue them alike.</hi> But why did I reinforce the obiection of the one, and conceale the defence of the other? made in ſo renouned a place, and recorded by ſo venerable a perſon.</p>
               <p>For though I might appeale vnto the teſtimony of his Auditors, <hi>who remaine vnto this preſent;</hi> yet I will goe <hi>from
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:4291:24"/> the liuing to the dead,</hi> and inquire, what is deliuered, and commended, by <note n="u" place="margin">Jn reſp. ad <hi>Camp.</hi> pag. <hi>656.657.</hi>
                  </note> M. Doctor <hi>Humfrey,</hi> vnto all poſterity, in this behalfe. But becauſe it might be tedious vnto you, to recite the whole paſſage, I will ſelect one parcell therof; to wit, that his Grace, hauing ſundry wayes refelled this calumnious imputation, did finally <hi>ſweare, by inuocation of the bleſſed Trinity, the</hi> FATHER, <hi>the creator of all things, the</hi> SON, <hi>the iudge of all the world, the</hi> HOLY GHOST, <hi>the comforter of vs all, that, ſo far as he could remember, or poſſibly recall to mind, this pretended anſwere, concerning the ancient Fathers, neuer fell from him in earneſt, nor inieſt.</hi> What can you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire more, for your ſatisfaction, in charity, or in reaſon? <hi>Varius dicit, Scaurus negat: vtri creditis?</hi> when <hi>Varius</hi> accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Scaurus</hi> of treaſon, in a profuſe, and copious ſpeech; <hi>Scaurus</hi> replied briefly: <hi>Varius ſaith it, Scaurus denieth it: whom do you belieue?</hi> Likewiſe; <hi>Edmund Campian,</hi> a Ieſuite, hath ſaid thus, as you heare: <hi>Tobias Matthew,</hi> a Chriſtian, denieth it: nay more, hee ſweareth by the ſacred name of God, in the holy aſſembly of his Church, that he is iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly charged. Whom, then, doe you belieue? This was his <note n="x" place="margin">See Doct. <hi>Humfrey</hi> pag. <hi>657.</hi>
                  </note> own defence: I haue borrowed it from himſelfe, howbeit a great part of its efficacy, and force, is loſt in this conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.<note n="y" place="margin">Val. Max <hi>lib.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. <hi>in fine.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>In Demoſthene magna pars abeſt Demoſthenis cùm legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; non auditur.</hi> A great part of him is wanting, when he ſpeaketh by an others tongue: <hi>though</hi> (as <note n="z" place="margin">Jbid.</note> one ſaith of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenes) his worke, in it ſelfe alſo, is ſo ful, &amp; perfect, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be added vnto the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>VVEll, All this while I haue told you, <hi>what I haue done to God:</hi> yea, <hi>that, which I haue done vnto the leaſt of his ſeruants, I haue done alſo vnto himſelfe.</hi> It remaineth now, that J tell you, <hi>what God hath done to me.</hi> I ſay, what <hi>God</hi> hath done. For though I acknowledge gratefully, that ſom perſons of quality, &amp; worth, were inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in that good
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:4291:25"/> which hath ſucceeded vnto mee, according to his wiſhes, rather then mine owne; yet I acknowledge God, him onely to be the author of the ſame; and that He hath done it, out of his <hi>Mercy, Loue,</hi> and <hi>Grace.</hi> Wherfore, <hi>Come, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, all you that feare the Lord, and I will tell you, what he hath done vnto my ſoule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His firſt bleſſing vnto me was, Reuocation into my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue country; deare, becauſe a COVNTRY: more, Becauſe SVCH a country: the ſweetneſſe, and felicity whereof, is known better, <hi>carendo,</hi> then <hi>fruendo,</hi> by wanting it a while, then by enioying it alwayes: and ſo it is in euery temporall, or ſpirituall good.</p>
               <p>Here now, ſome wil imagine, that, either in my diſceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or in my reuerſion, or in both, my ends were drawn, rather <hi>ab vtili,</hi> then <hi>ab honeſto:</hi> that I ſerued my owne turne, in this returne: that I departed with the reſolution of <hi rend="sup">a</hi> 
                  <hi>Caeſar,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting vnto his mother, vpon taking of his leaue, <hi>Se, niſi Pontificem, non reuerſurum:</hi> ſo I, without a Benefice, or Dignity in the Church, would neuer returne into the Land.</p>
               <p>But as the manner of my returne (if it were fit to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in this place) might acquit mee fully, from the ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition of ſuch an impious deuice: ſo they, who had the beſt experience of my mind at that time, might then ſee, &amp; will yet confeſſe, that, in all probability, I framed no ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect in my thoughts: but that I was a real, ſubſtantial Papiſt: howſoeuer ſome men (led with an honeſt errour) haue ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to conceiue otherwiſe of my caſe.</p>
               <p>If the teſtimonies of eminent perſons, may be required; or admitted, in this kind; I would make choice of one, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly, aboue the reſt; to acknowledge whoſe kindnes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me, it is the leaſt recompence that I owe him, &amp; yet the greateſt, that I can make him for the ſame.</p>
               <p>He then doth know, that, vpon my return, I did expreſſe a great auerſion from this Church: pardon me: it was more: euen a deteſtation thereof. And when hee would ſeeme to nouriſh ſome hope (aboue hope) of my reduction thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to;
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:4291:25"/> I did beſeech, and requeſt him, moſt affectionately, not to ſow his fauours vpon the conceit of ſuch an harueſt. For I was throughly acquainted with the nature, and quality of mine owne ſoile, too barren for ſuch fruit.</p>
               <p>Here, alſo, I may not forget, nor conceale, his anſwere vnto me; for it was full of comfort, and conſcience: to wit, that I ſhould not be allured, nor preſſed [by his maieſties royal fauour and grace; of which he conceiued good hope] otherwiſe, then I had the ſecret teſtimony, and certain per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of mine owne heart.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, out of his noble, and religious diſpoſition, he perſiſted ſtill in his pious, and charitable worke. J ſay <hi>pious,</hi> and <hi>charitable.</hi> For what other aduantage did hee ſeeke, or could he find, then that, which S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> did long ſince, in a like caſe? <hi>Quid quaero? Quo fructu quaero?</hi> ſaith <note n="b" place="margin">Co<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. de <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>E<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ito.</hi>
                  </note> hee of a <hi>Donatiſt,</hi> in his time. What is it, which I ſeeke? Or, with what profit, doe I ſeeke it? He anſwereth; <hi>Vt aliquando d<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur mihi: Frater tuus mortuus erat, &amp; reuixit; perierat, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentus est:</hi> that once it may be ſaid vnto mee, <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 15.31.</note> 
                  <hi>Thy Brother was dead, and is aliue againe; he was loſt, but he is found.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this end, and purpoſe, J was recommended by his ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall care (but againſt my will: for I loued my owne euill, and feared the remedy thereof) vnto the Reuerend Deane of <hi>Pauls;</hi> a man ſo rarely qualified with Morall, and Intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual, vertues, that his worth doth no leſſe verifie his name, then his name doth ſignifie his worth. And this I eſteeme one of the greateſt (if not the greateſt) bleſſings of God vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, that, when I was as blinde in the eies of my minde, as <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 9.</note> S. <hi>Paul</hi> was in the eies of his body (yea of minde alſo) I ſhould be ſent (or rather brought) vnto this worthy <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niah</hi> [<hi>nubes Domini,</hi> the cloud of the Lord; ſo it is by inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation] for the reſtitution of my ſight, and bee mollified againe, by the ſweet ſhowres of his learned, and iudicious diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>Thus, after a long, vnhappy flight, I returned, with <hi>Noahs</hi> 
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 8.9.</note> Doue, into the <hi>Arke,</hi> which J once forſooke, and fluttered vpon the ſwelling waters of <hi>Babylon,</hi> which can giue no
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:4291:26"/> true reſt (but a Lethargie) vnto the ſoule. Finally, after a long, and tedious motion, I found reſt, and repoſe vnto my ſoule, in the ſame center, wherein I was ſeated from my ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and more happie, yeeres. <hi>This was the Lords doing, and it is maruellous in mine eies.</hi> What enſued? <hi>Mutantur, ſuſcipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur,</hi> ſaith <note n="f" place="margin">Vbi ſup<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>à.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> of the <hi>Donatiſts:</hi> They relinquiſh their opinion, the Church receiueth them into her vnion againe. So it was with mee; ſuch was the gratious fauour of God, ſuch the great indulgencie of his Church.</p>
               <p>You will, peraduenture, demand now; Vpon what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuall motiues I did returne, ſince I had ſome (in my wrong apprehenſion) to depart?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I will ſpeake the truth in Chriſt, I will not lie; my conſcience bearing me witneſſe in the holy Ghoſt.</hi> The only thing, wherein J did intend to conforme my ſelfe vnto the deſire of my friends, and will of my ſuperiours, was, to take <hi>the oath of Allegiance,</hi> as it is truly, and iuſtly ſtyled. For what elſe doth it containe, in the ſubſtance thereof, but a ciuill obedience, and faith, due, from ſubiects, vnto their Soueraigne Lord, by lawes diuine, and humane, yea founded in the very prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Nature, and Reaſon? Wherein I did obſerue, FIRST, how carefully the matter of State is heere diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from controuerſie of Religion. In which regard, it was the determinate pleaſure of his ſacred <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>See his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties</hi> Premo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to all Chriſtian Monarkes, &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 9.</note> Maieſtie, to eaſe the burden of the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> not requiring them to ſweare, that <hi>the Pope hath no authoritie to excommunicate his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to ſubiect him vnto a ſpirituall cenſure,</hi> but that <hi>the power of ſuch excommunication cannot, by any meanes, extend it ſelfe vnto the preiudice of his royall Life, or Crowne.</hi> SE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CONDLY then, I obſerued thereupon, that though there are ſome circumſtantiall points in this oath, vpon which ſome <hi>Papiſts</hi> doe principally inſiſt, for their refuſall thereof, yet that they did, heerein, but gloze with his Maieſtie, and vſe a ſpecious pretenſe to reiect the ſubſtance of the Oath; which, being abſtracted from all circumſtances, and acceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries therein, hath this principall iſſue: to wit, that <hi>the Pope hath no power, directly, nor indirectly, to depoſe his Maieſtie
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:4291:26"/> from the right of his Crowne, nor to expoſe his perſon vnto the perill of his life.</hi> So that the refuſall of this Oath (thus ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: and this is the true ſenſe thereof) by any popiſh ſubiect in this land, doth demonſtrate euidently, and expreſly, that he wanteth meanes, and not a mind, to dethrone our moſt gratious Soueraigne Lord, the KING (whom God preſerue, to his honour, and our comfort) yea (which I tremble to ſpeake, but he would not feare to doe) to take away his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious life, with ſacrilegious hands, ſpecially if ſuch be the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of <note n="h" place="margin">See this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by D. <hi>Morton,</hi> in his encounter againſt <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> lib <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>2. §. 6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>our Lord God, the</hi> POPE.</p>
               <p>To ſhew, therefore, my zealous, and hearty deteſtation of ſuch impious, and execrable doctrine (ſent continually from <hi>Rome,</hi> ſowen plentifully in the hearts of <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects: and this ſeed will grow into an harueſt of lamentable combuſtion, if our iuſt lawes be not enliuened by a ſeuere execution, in this behalfe) I tooke this Oath, vpon ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deliberation, and aduice, that I dare confidently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce: <hi>Whatſoeuer ſubiect in this Land doth pertinaciouſly refuſe to ſweare allegiance vnto the King, according to the ſenſe and ſubſtance of this oath, he is a</hi> TRAITOR, <hi>in his heart, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the life and ſoueraigntie of his Prince.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now, as, by this act, I gaue teſtification of my loialty vnto the State, ſo, withall, I incurred the ſuſpition of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and apoſtaſie, with others. Why? what was my offence? Oh a great, yea a double offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce againſt his Holineſſe; which euery one, that taketh this oath, muſt neceſſarily commit. FIRST, he denieth the infallibility of the Popes iudgement: yea hee admitteth farther, that the Pope erreth, not onely <hi>materially,</hi> but <hi>formally;</hi> not in <hi>fact,</hi> but in <hi>faith:</hi> alſo, not as a <hi>priuate Doctor,</hi> but as <hi>publike Paſtor</hi> of the Church. Finally, that this his error is <hi>execrable</hi> and <hi>damnable,</hi> according to the tenor and purport of the oath.</p>
               <p>Now if any man be deſirous to know, how farre the Pope was intereſſed in the prohibition of this oath, let him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult the <note n="*" place="margin">To the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes of England.</note> ſecond Breue of <hi>Paulus</hi> 5. dated 10. Calends of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember, 1607. Wherein he ſaith preciſely: <hi>We haue ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commanded you, that, by no meanes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you ſhould take it:</hi> againe,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:4291:27"/> 
                  <hi>our Apoſtolike letters, concerning the prohibition of the Oath, were written, not only vpon our proper motion, and of our certaine knowledge, but alſo after long and weighty deliberation, vſed concerning all thoſe things which are contained in them</hi> [the ſaid Letters] <hi>and that for this cauſe, you are bound fully to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> reiecting all interpretation, perſwading to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And this is our meere, pure, and perfect will,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>SECONDLY, he denieth the Popes power, either <hi>directly,</hi> or <hi>indirectly, temporally,</hi> or <hi>ſpiritually,</hi> ouer our dread Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord, the KING, to be ſuch, that he may, ſentential<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, depoſe him from his Crowne, abſolue his ſubiects from their alleageance (though due vnto him by the bonds of <hi>Nature,</hi> and pledged vnto him, farther, by the obligation of an <hi>Oath</hi>) and inable them to beare armes againſt him, or, by any meanes, to depriue him of his Regality, and Life.</p>
               <p>Theſe, then, are the two offences, which I haue commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt the dignitie of the triple Crowne. But why is that ſo capitall with our <hi>Engliſh Catholikes,</hi> which the <hi>French</hi> do ſo freely and liberally maintaine?</p>
               <p>Not long before my departure out of <hi>France,</hi> I addreſſed myſelf vnto a paire of learned <note n="i" place="margin">Meſſicurs, le Maſtre, <hi>&amp;</hi> le Marchand.</note> 
                  <hi>Dominicans</hi> in <hi>Roan,</hi> doctors of the <hi>Sorborn</hi> in <hi>Paris:</hi> of whom, as I deſired ſome exact in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions concerning this Oath, ſo I deliuered his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties <note n="k" place="margin">Apol<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gia pr<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> iuramento Fidelitatis, &amp;c.</note> booke into their hands, for their better information in this behalfe. They read it with expedition, applauding the great wiſedome, and excellent knowledge of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; proteſting alſo, that, as the <hi>Oath,</hi> for the matter, and ſubſtance of it, was agreeable vnto the Catholike faith, ſo, for the occaſion and inducement of the ſame, it was moſt expedient, and neceſſary, for the preſeruation of his royall State They added farther, that this extenſion of the Papall power ouer Chriſtian Princes, was <hi>dogma Tranſalpinum,</hi> an Italian conceit (for they obſerue a difference betwixt the <hi>Romane</hi> COVRT, and the <hi>Romane</hi> CHVRCH) which a true <hi>French</hi> Catholike heart doth religiouſly abhor. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they aduiſed mee to take the ſaid oath, as themſelues alſo, and all <hi>French</hi> men, would doe in the like caſe,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:4291:27"/> were it required at their hands.</p>
               <p>But our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Catholikes are (for the greater part) of an hotter conſtitution, more affected vnto the climats of <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spaine.</hi> Which I ſpeake with commiſeration of my own Country; not to the diſreputation of thoſe great and mighty Nations: the eies whereof God will open, in his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time to ſhake off this <hi>Babylonian</hi> yoke. For which, I haue better euidence, then <note n="l" place="margin">Comment. in Gen. <hi>15.16.</hi> in fine.</note> 
                  <hi>Pererius</hi> a Ieſuit hath for the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity &amp; vaſtation of <hi>England;</hi> puſhing at vs like an <note n="m" place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 21.11.</note> hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Zidkiiah:</hi> but with the like ſucceſſe (I hope) as his falſe brethren did not long before, who prophecied thus vnto the King of <hi>Spaine:</hi> 
                  <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Go and proſper, for the Lord ſhall deliuer</hi> England <hi>into thy hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You haue heard, now, the cauſe and beginning of my alienation from my <hi>Engliſh-Romane</hi> friends. Was it not iuſt and good? For what a deſperate connexion is there betwixt theſe doctrines? FIRST, <hi>The Pope hath an infallible iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (as Pope) to determine, what is hereſie, obliging all men to reſt, ſecurely, in his ſentence.</hi> Yea <note n="o" place="margin">Analyſ. fidei lib <hi>8.</hi> cap <hi>3.</hi> ad. obiect. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Gregorius de Valentia</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is ſo deeply infatuated with this vanity, that he feareth not to affirme; <hi>The Pope, whether he vſe diligence, or not, in defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſhall define infallibly, if he will define a controuerſie: and ſo, in truth, hee ſhall vſe the authority committed vnto him by Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The SECOND is, that, <hi>in caſe of hereſie he may depoſe the King, abſolue his ſubiects from obedience, and giue away his Crowne;</hi> as <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> gaue away the Crowne of <hi>England</hi> vnto the late King of <hi>Spaine:</hi> and this is one inſtance, which <note n="p" place="margin">Inſtitut. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. pars <hi>2.</hi> lib. <hi>11.</hi> c. <hi>5</hi> q. <hi>8.</hi> §. Pius quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que.</note> 
                  <hi>Azorius</hi> the Ieſuite, doth alleage, to prooue the tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie of the Papall power.</p>
               <p>Now, if the Pope haue <hi>infallibility of iudgement,</hi> in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, to determine, what is hereſie, and then a <hi>ſoueraigntie of power</hi> alſo, to dethrone, and murther any King for hereſie: iudge you how dangerous is the condition of our King, who valiantly reſiſteth his tyrannicall proceedings; &amp; how miſerable is their thraldome, who are inſlaued to the yoke of his power and will. Meane while, <note n="q" place="margin">2. <hi>Theſſ</hi> 2 <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>He ſitteth in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:4291:28"/> of God, ſhewing himſelfe that he is God:</hi> but yet, therein, ſhewing himſelfe to be, as he is, ANTICHRIST: <hi>whom the Lord ſhall conſume with the ſpirit of his mouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The conſideration of al which particulars (ſummoned vp together) did treat with me (as they may, and ought to doe, with any man, in my caſe) to ſhew greater equanimity in the reuiew of other points, now controuerſed, in Religion; and namely in thoſe FOVRE, which I haue mentioned <note n="*" place="margin">Pag 44.</note> before. Wherein, though I cannot acquaint you wholly how I did proceed, yet I will giue you ſome ouerture thereof, briefly as I paſſe.</p>
               <p>The FIRST was, concerning <hi>Purgatory,</hi> which I vtterly reiect, and renounce, as inglorious to the bloud of Chriſt, and troubleſome to the ſweete comfortable repoſe of our ſoules in him.</p>
               <p>The SECOND was, concerning ſome errors in the writings of our chiefe Diuines: of which point, I haue already gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vp a verdit againſt my ſelfe. I adde now farther, that ſuch errors in them (if truly noted by me) ſhould not reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably, remoue a man from the integrity of his faith, which dependeth vpon a more certaine principle and ground. Why ſhould the error of any MAN preiudice the eternall truth of GOD?</p>
               <p>But beyond all this; is there more ſincerity in the <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> that, in reſpect hereof, I ſhould ſubſcribe more readily vnto them? Truly ſuch was mine opinion: but the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate teſtimony of mine eies, and the deliberate iudgement of my reaſon, haue taught me to beleeue otherwiſe herein.</p>
               <p>For a copious teſtimony in this kind, I remit you vnto the late <note n="r" place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi> per totum.</note> 
                  <hi>Encounter</hi> of Maſter Doctor <hi>Morton</hi> againſt Maſter <hi>Parſons:</hi> and the rather, becauſe I haue compared each par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, from point to point, with the Authors themſelues, whence he doth produce the ſame: ſo that J am an ocular witnes of his fidelity therein, as alſo, throughout the whole courſe of that booke. There you ſhall finde <hi>Suarez</hi> (a grand Ieſuite) charged by <hi>Cumel</hi> (a learned <hi>Dominican</hi>) in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <hi>I am greeued to ſee how fraudulently they</hi> [Suarez Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lina,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:4291:28"/> &amp;c.] <hi>cite</hi> Driedo, <hi>vrging that, which he ſpake by way of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentation, or obiection, for his owne iudgement whereas</hi> Dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edo <hi>vſeth many arguments to confute that opinion.</hi> Againe; Zuarez <hi>citeth a ſentence of</hi> Soto, <hi>but leapeth ouer one part of it, leauing that out, which maketh againſt himſelfe.</hi> Againe, Suarez <hi>hath changed the word</hi> Praeordination (<hi>in</hi> S. Thomas) <hi>into</hi> Subordination, <hi>and expoundeth</hi> S. Thomas <hi>ſiniſterly. I cannot tell with what ſpirit he citeth</hi> Driedo, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heare further, how the great Cardinal <hi>Baronius</hi> is repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by ſome famous Diuines of Venice, <hi>viz. When</hi> Baronius <hi>intreateth of the immunity of the Clergy, and wanteth other ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, he diſliketh all hiſtorians. When he admitteth any, he ſing<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth out the words, which make for him: but theſe which make a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt him, he ſaith, were inſerted by others. There is a booke inti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuled,</hi> The errors of Baronius, <hi>wherein there are diſcouered more then twenty ſeuerall errors, which he hath commited about one ſtory,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Finally, heare the like accuſations, by them, againſt <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> himſelfe. <hi>He expoundeth</hi> Thomas <hi>contrary to his meaning. He imputeth a ſpeech vnto an Author, who yet doth affirme the contrary. He ſaith, that</hi> Nauarr <hi>holdeth thus, and thus, whereas he held the plaine contrary. It is no rare thing for his illustrious Lordſhippe, to cite Authors for an opinion, whereas they affirme the plaine contrary. He abuſeth the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of</hi> Gerſon. <hi>He falſly citeth a place of</hi> S. Hierome, <hi>who ſaith the plaine contrary. It greeueth me to ſee things imputed by</hi> Bellarmine, <hi>vnto the Fathers: the contrary whereof they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>For concluſion, let me acquaint you with one (I ſay but one, to ſpare you, not him) ſingular impoſture of <hi>Bellarmine</hi> againſt <hi>Caluin,</hi> and ſo I will diſmiſſe this point. The <note n="ſ" place="margin">Bellarm. de ſanct. beat. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi> §. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ſt igitur.</note> que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is; <hi>Whether the ſoules of holy men (diſſolued from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and ſtanding in need of no purgation) be admitted vnto the fruition of bleſſedneſſe, which conſisteth in the cleere viſion of God?</hi> It followeth. <hi>Some heretikes</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bellarmine) were of opinion, that the ſoules were reſerued in certaine receptacles, vnto the day of iudgement, where they ſaw not God, nor were
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:4291:29"/> bleſſed, otherwiſe, then in hope.</hi> What heretikes? <hi>Tertullian; Vigilantius,</hi> &amp;c. Be it ſo. Who elſe? He addeth, <hi>Iohn Caluin alſo hath the ſame errour.</hi> Where? <hi>Inſtitut.</hi> 3. booke, 20. chap. §. 20 What are the words? <note n="t" place="margin">Bellarm. ibid § E<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ndem habet, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Caluin doth ſay, that Chriſt alone, is gone into the Sanctuary of heauen, and that all others remaine in the Court: expecting there, vntill the conſummation of the world.</hi> Let vs make a triall now, whether <hi>Caluin</hi> bee guilty of this opinion, or <hi>Bellarmine</hi> calumnious in his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion.</p>
               <p>FIRST, then, for the opinion of <hi>Caluin</hi> in this matter, you ſhall finde, that he is ſingularly traduced therein. For a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many paſſages in his works, behold this one: <note n="u" place="margin">Caluin. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. Libertin. cap. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The ſoules of the faithfull, as ſoone as they are departed from this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, doe liue with God, and inioy the happineſſe of that kingdome,</hi> which is in heauen. <hi>Howbeit,</hi> ſaith he (and he ſaith it truly) <hi>God hath reſerued their perfect</hi> [conſummate] <hi>felicity, vntil the ſecond comming of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>SECONDLY, therefore, it may pleaſe you to conſider with me, how vnworthily, and ſlanderouſly <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forceth this error vpon <hi>Caluin,</hi> out of the aſſigned place. I finde indeed, that <hi>Caluin</hi> doth, there, expreſly affirme; <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus, ſanctuarium coeli ingreſſus, ad conſummationem vſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſeculo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, ſolus populi, eminùs in atrio reſidentis, vota ad Deum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert:</hi> that is; Chriſt being entred into the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, vnto the end of the world, doth alone carry (or preſent) the praiers of the people, remaining a farre off in the <hi>Court,</hi> vnto God.</p>
               <p>Now obſerue the fraud. Of whom is the queſtion? Of the dead, or of the liuing? Of the DEAD: to wit, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſoules of them, who are fallen aſleepe in Chriſt. And of them <hi>Caluin</hi> is charged by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> to ſay, that <hi>they are not in heauen, &amp;c.</hi> and, for a proofe, he hath alleaged this place. But of whom doth <hi>Caluin</hi> there intreat? of the dead, or of the liuing? Of the LIVING: for ſo doth the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> whole diſcourſe import. As in the words a little before; <hi>Membrorum omnium, adhuc in terra laborantium, mutuae, pro ſe inuicem, orationes aſcendunt ad caput, quod praeceſſit in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:4291:29"/> coelum,</hi> &amp;c. The mutuall prayers of all the members, yet la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring here vpon the earth, aſcend vnto the Head, which is gone before vs into heauen. Likewiſe, in the very place it <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſelfe: for <hi>Caluin</hi> ſaith, that Chriſt being in the <hi>Sanctuarie,</hi> carrieth vp, vnto God, the praiers of the people, remaining in the <hi>Court.</hi> What people? the <hi>liuing:</hi> for the office of the Saints <hi>departed</hi> is not to <hi>pray,</hi> but to <hi>praiſe</hi> the Lord. Again, immediately after, euen in the very next words vnto thoſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth ſo fraudulently cite: <hi>Quantum ad Sanctos attinet, qui carne mortui, in Chriſto viuunt,</hi> &amp;c. As for the Saints, who, being dead in the fleſh, liue in [or with] Chriſt, &amp;c. Which words, as they doe plainely ſhew, that <hi>Caluin</hi> ſpake before, of the liuing, and not of the dead, ſo likewiſe they doe fully conuince the falſity of this preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded crime. Wherein the colluſion of <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alſo, becauſe <hi>Caluin</hi> doth not ſay (as the Cardinall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puteth vnto him) that <hi>Chriſt, alone, is gone into the Sanctuary of Heauen, he</hi> &amp; none els: but that <hi>he, being entred into it, doth alone</hi> (he, and none elſe) preſent the praiers of the<note n="x" place="margin">Who are liuing in this world, and are not in the <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary</hi> of Heauen.</note> people vnto God: ſo that, vnto him, alone, the office of a <hi>Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour</hi> doth peculiarly belong. And this is the ſubiect of <hi>Caluins</hi> diſpute.</p>
               <p>But I leaue this ſecond point (wherein I haue too much abuſed your patience) and come vnto the THIRD: which was, concerning <hi>Vocation vnto ſacred Miniſterie, in this Church.</hi> Wherein I know, that the <hi>power of order</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete in all reſpects. In reſpect of the perſons calling; that they had ſufficient ability to conferre it. In reſpect of the perſons called; that they had actuall capacity to receiue it. In reſpect of the vocation itſelfe; that it had no ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall defect, in Matter, nor in Forme. As alſo, that the <hi>power of Iuriſdiction,</hi> here is entire: that it hath not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deriuation from the Pope, but floweth from God, by the Church, by the Magiſtrate, by the people; differently, but truly, as I am able and willing to proue, when good op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity ſhall ſerue, and iuſt occaſion ſhall require.</p>
               <p>Concerning the FOVRTH, and laſt point: namely the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:4291:30"/> 
                  <hi>Church;</hi> I know, and acknowledge, that God had a Church alwaie; that it was <note n="y" place="margin">D. Field. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> viſible; that though many erred there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, yet not all: or, at the leaſt, not ſo, but that there remained a ſubſtance of faith, ſufficient vnto ſaluation. Finally, that as a generall <hi>Reformation</hi> was expedient, and neceſſary, ſo our particular was orderly, good, and iuſt.</p>
               <p>In a word therefore, to acquaint you with my totall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity vnto the doctrine of this Church (contained in the 39. <hi>Articles of Religion</hi>) I haue ſubmitted my ſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, by profeſſion of mouth, by ſubſcription of hand, by conſent of heart. In this faith J deſire to ſpend, and end, the courſe of my life; to the honour of GOD, the benefit of his CHVRCH, the comfort of my owne ſoule.</p>
               <p>Now I may ſay ioyfully with <hi>Dauid;</hi> 
                  <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Returne vnto thy reſt, ô my ſoule; for the Lord hath beene beneficiall vnto thee.</hi> Or with <hi>Simeon;</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 2.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, now let reſt thou thy ſeruant depart in peace, according to thy word: for mine eyes haue ſeene thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</hi> I loſt thee, but thou didſt not looſe me; I fled from thee, and thou didſt ſeeke me; I erred, and thou didſt reduce me; I was blind, and thou didſt illuminate me; I was harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and thou didſt mollifie me; ſo I returned (by thee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee) and thou haſt receiued me againe. Therfore I will exalt thy name for euer, and humble my ſelfe with <hi>Dauid,</hi> befor thee, ſaying:<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86.11.12.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Teach me thy way, ô Lord, and I will walke in thy truth: knit my hart vnto thee, that I may feare thy name. I will praiſe thee, ô Lord my God, with all my heart: yea, I will glorifie thy name for euer. For great is thy mercy toward me: &amp; thou haſt deliuered my ſoule from the nethermoſt hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus you ſee (Brethren) in part, what <hi>God hath done vnto my ſoule,</hi> as alſo what I owe vnto him for his <hi>mercy, loue,</hi> and <hi>grace:</hi> and what I ſhall perform vnto him, for the ſame, by the aſſiſtance of his Spirit. Hereunto I will adioin a briefe remonſtrance of my duty vnto the CHVRCH, of my loi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty vnto the KING: finally, I will conclude with a peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and promiſe vnto your ſelues.</p>
               <p>The FIRST is, my duety vnto the <hi>Church</hi> of God, in this flouriſhing Iland, or rather little world; the glory whereof
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:4291:30"/> I haue laboured to obſcure, with my vnfortunate, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduiſed pen. But as <note n="c" place="margin">See Auguſt. epiſt. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Stefichorus</hi> loſt his eies, by diſpraiſing the faire <hi>Helena</hi> of Greece, &amp; recouered them, by praiſing her againe: ſo, to reobtaine my former ſight, I wil expend al the faculties that I haue, in aduancing the dignity, &amp; luſtre of this inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parable Church: <hi>incomparable</hi> in many reſpects, but ſpecially in two. <hi>Firſt,</hi> in the excellency of preaching the Goſpell. For as <hi>God hath giuen the word, and great is the multitude of Preachers:</hi> ſo, in their gifts, matter, and manner of preaching, ſingular alſo is the perfection of Preachers in this Land. <hi>Secondly,</hi> in the Common praier, and Liturgy, a iewel ſo pretious, that it cannot be valued at too high a rate.</p>
               <p>The SECOND thing was, my loialty vnto our gratious Soueraigne Lord, and King, whoſe mercy towards me, hath been very great, in pardoning my offences, which, mediatly (at the leaſt) did touch his roiall Selfe. The Subiects, whom I grieued, are vnder his dition: the Lawes which I violated, are vnder his adminiſtration: the Church which I ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized, is vnder his protection: the Faith, which I impugned, is vnder his DEFENCE, by common right, and ſpeciall ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle. So that all theſe, coniunctiuely, might plead for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge from his princely hands, ſince <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee beareth not the ſword in vaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, as J ſaid before, his Highneſſes mercy hath bin very great vnto me, in making me an example of his clemency, which, in truth, is ſo naturall vnto Him, that He (as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <note n="e" place="margin">Senec. de Clem lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Augustus</hi>) may well be called <hi>Parens Patriae,</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his Country, becauſe (as <hi>Seneca</hi> teſtifieth of <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus) apparet illum dare poenas, cùm exigit:</hi> It appeares that He doth ſuffer puniſhment Himſelfe, when (by compulſion) He doth take it of another.</p>
               <p>It is my ſpeciall obligation, therefore, beyond a common duty, to pray (yea I pray now, and beſeech you all to ioyne your hearts with mine, lifting them vp vnto GOD, for Him) that his Maieſty may inioy a peaceable raigne, a proſperous eſtate, and obtaine a bleſſed end, after a long, and happy life; that He may be tranſlated, from an earthly, vnto an heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:4291:31"/> kingdome, where the glorious Lambe ſitteth, <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Apoc.</hi> 19.16.</note> 
                  <hi>The King of Kings, and Lord of Lords<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> that, as now, he raigneth <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 8, 15.</note>
                  <hi>by him;</hi> ſo there he may raigne <hi>with him,</hi> in that happineſſe, which hath no miſery, in that abundance, which hath no want, in that ſecurity, which hath no feare, in that eternity, which hath no end. Amen.</p>
               <p>Now THIRDLY, and laſtly, I turne my ſpeech vnto you, deare, and welbeloued Countrimen, in whoſe audience, and with whoſe patience, I haue made a full and free confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of my error. I haue not hid it (for thereby I ſhould hide God from me, not me from God) I haue not hid it, I ſay, by <hi>Negation,</hi> nor by <hi>Extenuation,</hi> nor by <hi>Iuſtification</hi> thereof, remembring what was <note n="h" place="margin">Februar. <hi>10.</hi> by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Kitſon</hi> of Peterhouſe in Cambridge,</note> lately deliuered here, in the proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of a Text, well choſen, and excellently handled: <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 28.13.</note> 
                  <hi>He that hideth his ſinnes, ſhall not proſper: but he that confeſſeth, and forſaketh them, ſhall haue mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for your charity towards me, I cannot doubt, but that, at the leaſt, you will eſteem of me, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> did ſometimes iudge of <hi>Oneſimus, Philemons</hi> ſeruant: <note n="k" place="margin">Philem. verſ. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>It may be that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted for a ſeaſon, that thou ſhouldeſt receiue him for euer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for me, I truſt in God (by the gratious aſſiſtance of his holy ſpirit) ſo to comport my ſelf in the whole courſe of my ſtudies, and actions, that, with iuſt application, you may call vnto your remembrance that, which S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, a little <note n="l" place="margin">Ibid. verſ. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> before, of that fugitiue ſeruant: <hi>He was vnprofitable in times paſt, vnto thee, but now profitable both vnto thee, and me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore, I requeſt you, Brethren, to praiſe God, with me, and for me, who hath thus extended his <hi>Mercy, Loue,</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> towards me, <hi>when I was dead in ſinne.</hi> Pray him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that I may vſe his bleſſings, to the honour of his name, and benefit of his Church. Finally, I beſeech him for you, and my ſelfe, that we all may haue, for the end of our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, his glory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the rule, his word; for the fruit of our faith, the ſaluation of our ſoules through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord: to whom with the Father, and the bleſſed ſpirit of both, be aſcribed all maieſty, power, and dominion, in heauen, and in earth, now, and for euer: Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4291:31"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
